<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Yunchtime</title>
  
  <subtitle>a jaunt to there and now</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
  <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Lex Berman</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reyes Cárdenas and the Moons of Mars</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/reyes-cardenas-and-the-moons-of-mars/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/reyes-cardenas-and-the-moons-of-mars/</id>
    <published>2017-09-17T20:33:27.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Altermundos_cover_sm.jpg" alt="" width="660" height="511"></p><p>Recently I checked out a copy of <a href="http://amzn.to/2xd8Kum" target="_blank" rel="external">Altermundos, Latin@ Speculative Literature and Popular Culture</a> from the library.  It contains many fascinating and important essays on the history and current state of Latin@ spec fic, and introduced me to the ground-breaking work of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_E._Anzald%C3%BAa" target="_blank" rel="external">Gloria Anzaldúa</a>, who wrote about <em>nepantla</em> (the in-betweenness of worlds) and those beings: <em>nepantleras</em> who traverse that no-man’s land.</p><p>Another author mentioned in the book was Reyes Cárdenas, a San Antonio poet and author of some short satirical science fiction poems called <em>Los Pachucos y La Flying Saucer</em>.   For some reason this title appealed to me, and I strayed out of the proper feminista struggles represented in <em>Altermundos</em> into the sardonic poems of a macho, an eternal walker of <em>el barrio</em>, who spoke to me easily and in the very language of my own ill-spent youth in Albuquerque.</p><blockquote><p>You young punks will not remember</p><p>when the pinto poets emerged</p><p>upon the scene machine,</p><p>a toda maquina,</p><p>the knives, the bullets of the words</p><p>they were shooting from the hip.</p><p>Ricardo Sánchez, raulsalinas,</p><p>whatever their crimes</p><p>they turned into rhymes,</p><p>Hechizospells from hell,</p><p>the iron bars that held raul</p><p>and his raza in the mind jail.</p><p>When the pinto poets looked in the mirror,</p><p>they didn’t see themselves —</p><p>they saw all of us!</p></blockquote><p>Barefoot, stepping on goat heads, and riding bicycles for fifty miles in the relentless sun, there was probably a lot of my own experience that was shared with Reyes over in San Antonio; though to tell the truth I was a not only a double-outcast but a triple-outcast.   I got shit not just from the Whites and the Mexicans.   I got shit from the Gringos at Highland High, and the Chicanos from Martineztown, and Los Indios (who kicked me around for being a gringo).  What saved me from being a quadruple-outcast, at Albuqueurque High, turned out to be the Mexican illegals who played on the soccer team.  Those <em>vatos</em> were pretending to be teenagers with fake IDs, some of them in their mid-twenties, having crawled through barbed wire, swum through flash-flood arroyos, living on nothing but dreams and radioactive dust as they infiltrated the border and made their way to the South Valley.   They were the only people as desperate and hungry as I was, and we knew by instinct that we were <em>carnales</em>.</p><p>Nobody ever thought that a white kid could be so poor, as he sat under a tree reading piles of books.  But that didn’t stop them, paradoxically, from spitting on him for wearing ragged clothes full of holes bought at Salvation Army, or kicking him out of school because his hair was long and tangled.   In those days of the early 1970s, Albuquerque was still in the throes of the late 60s, and the reactionary forces were in full swing.   Buzz cuts and gangs were the standard social reality, whereas long dreadlocks had never been seen, forget about on the head of <em>gringo</em> punk Jew from Chicago walking down the halls of Jefferson Junior High School!</p><p>So yeah, when Reyes writes his stuff, it just flows with a normalcy that is uncanny in my brain.</p><p>Even though I escaped the Land of Enchantment and rambled &#8212; with <em>nada que perder</em> &#8212; all over the globe, still those days get burned forever into one’s psyche and subconscious.   Like Reyes says:</p><blockquote><p>It’s no longer nomás Yogi Berra’s déjà vu.</p><p>You’ve become a stranger</p><p>in your own land once again!</p></blockquote><p>And possibly that is one of the major simpaticos of la cienca ficción, when your back is against the wall and you are denied any place in a world of putas and pendejos who think they have some social status and ownership from which you are going to be evicted:  yeah, there are pretty much only the realms of inner and outer space left to set up camp.</p><blockquote><p> with so few jobs</p><p>back on Earth</p><p>for a man of his color</p><p>since the new edicts</p><p>became the law</p><p>of the land,</p><p><strong>space had become</strong></p><p> <strong>his only option</strong>.</p></blockquote><p>Well, the only thing I can say about this great book, <a href="http://amzn.to/2yhMMFk" target="_blank" rel="external">Reyes Cardenas: Chicano Poet 1970-2010</a>, is <em>gracias primo</em> for writing it!</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/ReyesCardenasCover_sm.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="767"></p><p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Altermundos_cover_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;660&quot; height=&quot;511&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="poetry" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/poetry/"/>
    
      <category term="identity" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/identity/"/>
    
      <category term="sabroso" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/sabroso/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The mystique of Keleck</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-mystique-of-keleck/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-mystique-of-keleck/</id>
    <published>2017-07-05T00:31:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first taste of any artwork associated with Keleck (<em>aka</em> Kelek), was at Boskone this year, where Andy Gelas brought my attention to two French paperback editions of Conan.   These were <em>Conan Le Guerrier</em>, and <em>Conan Le Cimmerian</em>, in the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titres/SF" target="_blank" rel="external">Titres SF editions</a> from the early 1980s.   Needless to say, the eye-popping contrast in red and black, and the the purity of design in these covers hit me like a sucker-punch in a Philip Marlowe story.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF40_Conan_Guerrier_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="809"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF54_Conan_Cimmerian_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="827"></p><p>&nbsp;</p><p><em>Le Cimmerian</em> has a pure movie-poster effect, with that smashing red background, and the bare skin of the figures has a smooth air-brushed look, while the tightly delineated designs on the metal are all perfectly highlighted.   The first thing I noticed about <em>Le Guerrier</em> is the darkness of the figure, of the rich draperies, of the stairwell vanishing into shadow.   The hair is certainly done the same way as <em>Le Cimmerian</em>:  frizzy threads in direct highlight against the background.  But in <em>Le Guerrier</em>, the eyes, the skin, the deliberate brushstrokes on the wall, and the marble steps; they have a very different aesthetic from the super-slick air-brushing of <em>Le Cimmerian</em>.  What is going on here?</p><a id="more"></a><p>My first discovery is that Kelek, the artist, was the partner and collaborator of Jean-Michel Nicollet, and that they painted dozens (if not hundreds!) of illustrations together.  Many of these are marvelous!</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF23_Conan_Sabreur_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="819"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF12_LaJungleNeu_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="820"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF10_PriveDuCosmos_410px.jpg" alt="" width="411" height="671"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Titres-SF_1_LeHommeCreaUnDieu_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="820"></p><p>The collaboration of Kelek (or Keleck) and Nicollet are attributed as cover artists for many (if not all!) of the titles in the paperback series: Titres SF, considered by many to be the best ever cover illustrations in France.  The covers in this series are all imbued with classical references, as well as dadaist absurdity and intense hues from the Pop Art spectrum.  Who were these amazing artists?</p><p>From various sources, it is easy to track down Nicollet, who was born in Lyon in 1944.  He studied art and developed a style of acrylic painting full of dark, strange, and supernatural images, which lent itself to the emerging crowd of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%A9tal_hurlant" target="_blank" rel="external"><em>Metal Hurlant</em></a> in the late 1970s.   However, on Nicollet’s French-language Wikipedia page, there is only one mention of Keleck, as his co-author on the books:  <em>Le Rejeton de l’univers</em> (1980)  and <em>Ersatz</em> (1981).    This is strange, because many of the other references to Nicollet invariably refer to his “partnership” with Keleck.    But who was Keleck?</p><p>According to one brief biography, Keleck, was also from Lyon, born there in 1946.   Her <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keleck" target="_blank" rel="external">Wikipedia page</a> characterizes Keleck illustrations as “peopled by pale beings who are extremely strange and glacial.”   She is described as self-taught &#8212; an auto-didact &#8212; and several fannish reviews claim that she brought a 70’s punk defiance into her art.</p><p>However, on deeper study, the first books published by Kelleck, were illustrations, I should say paintings, for Children’s stories.   See for example her magnificent cover for <em>Lubie ou pas Lubie</em> (1975), which translates roughly as “A Whim or not a Whim,” although it was published in English under the title <em>Crazy Days</em>.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/LUBIE-OU-PAS-LUBIE_cvr_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="843"></p><p>This is hardly a 70s punk aesthetic!   This is an <em>hommage</em> to the classics:  to Henri Rousseau, of course, with the svelte jaguar in front of the foliage.   But there is also something else going on in this painting, the animals are all in action.  Whereas a Rousseau beast has an implication of energy, his canvases are always in a surreal moment of stasis, a half lucid state in between reality and dream.</p><p>Keleck enters the same surrealistic realm with the perfect attention to detail, but in her cover painting for <em>Crazy Days</em> there is no restful complaisance;  there is, instead, a mischievous rabbit hopping on the head of the beast, literally tweaking its nose and bolting away.  The jaguar is roused, but not furious… more like annoyed by the capricious rascal that arrives and is gone in a flash.   The background of this painting offers some more surrealistic detail:  those fat tendrils of plants look almost like something from Fernand Leger, while the blob-like substances rising among them seem to be super-enlarged fish eggs &#8212; jungle caviar!</p><p>The interior of the book is just as wonderful:  take a close look at this odd masterpiece, where a jaguar-headed man is boxing with a bunny-headed woman!</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/LUBIE-OU-PAS-LUBIE_int_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="417"></p><p>The man, in his jaguar skinned leotard, and the woman in her tight jaguar pants are posing, in this view, rather than actually boxing.   But what a perfect opportunity for the bunny-woman to show off her giant black pearl necklace, her Coco buckled belt,  and her arm length black silk gloves.   There is an artifice to this painting, an unreality similar to a Rene Magritte painting, which is mixed up with an Adams family gothic fashion sense, and slowed down with an opium-pipe haze.</p><p>If this book appeared in 1975, I would be willing to bet that <a href="http://yunchtime.net/?p=344" target="_blank" rel="external">Carlos Ochagavia</a> saw it, and took off running with those glowing piles of egg-like orbs in his Agent Flandry covers (beginning some four years later).</p><p>But let’s go back to Keleck and try to isolate her style from that of Nicollet.   If we take a look at another early book she painted, <em>Le Lion</em> (1978), you’ve got to love the humor of the gazelle, showing us it’s ass!  And the mother baboon, with one eye bizarrely rolled upwards.  Why not the baboon’s ass, rather than the gazelle?  Isn’t that how it is always done?  Another tweak to the nose!</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/LeLion_Kessel_illo_500ox.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="349"></p><p>Then there is the stunning cover!  A magnificent lion is standing in the grass, while strange fan-like trees grow from a crystal blue lake.  Overhead, in the twilight sky:  bats!   <strong>Five bats soaring in front of the moon and the stars.</strong>   Marvelous!</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/lion_cover_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="661"></p><p><a href="https://janine.ofilduweb.com/publications/kelek/" target="_blank" rel="external">Janine Kotwica</a> tells us that Kelek’s real name was Jacqueline Barse.  Kotwica describes Kelek as follows:  “practiced various artistic trades: display designer, graphic designer, modeler of the magazine Ah! Nana, interior designer, drawing and illustration teacher, set designer and costume designer for theater and contemporary dance, creates stage make-ups that she first experiences on her own, <strong>cultivating an unforgettable look Of Egyptian priestess</strong>.”</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Keleck_aka_JacquelineBarse.jpg" alt="" width="410" height="554"></p><p>Certainly that look was true, captured in the only photos that I could find of her so far.   The photo above was taken by Robert Doisneau (the photographer famous for his photo <a href="https://iconicphotos.org/2009/05/08/le-baiser-de-lhotel-de-ville/" target="_blank" rel="external"><em>Le baiser de l’hôtel de ville</em></a> ).   According to <a href="http://www.artnet.fr/artistes/robert-doisneau/keleck-illustratrice-AQETVO1FVjYFviJ2rqIWIA2" target="_blank" rel="external">ArtNet</a>, the photo was taken around 1970, and an original black and white print has a value of 1000 Euros.</p><p>So that was Keleck?  Posing in the frame between heavy curtains, her eyes are heavily blackened with kohl in the “Egyptian” style.   Though if you ask me, these are much more like the eyes of a <a href="http://richardsala.tumblr.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Richard Sala</a> villain, than the traceries of an Eye of Horus.   Her lips are heavily rouged, and her hair is tied up in a severe, flattened mass, with an almost feline angle on either side, like the laid back ears of a giant cat ready to pounce.</p><p>Notice the intense backlight framing her head and shoulders, throwing the left side of her face into shadow, while a fill light on the right reveals her incredibly pale face, no doubt powdered to a ghostly white!  Is that a real or artificial mole at the apex of the cheekbone?  The foreground light also reveals Kelek’s tapering delicate fingers, most of them wearing chunky, oddly ornate rings.   She is lightly tweaking a cigaret holder in her right hand, as if raising it to take a puff, and her raised hand shows the white starched cuff of her shirt sleeve, which is fastened at the neck with a man’s Carnaby Street striped tie.  It’s also a men’s single-breasted jacket she is wearing, with a flower &#8212; <em>is that an orchid!</em> &#8212; in the <em>boutonnierre</em>.</p><p>The only thing I can conclude from this photo is that it is a perfectly staged performance.   The whole photo is half shadow, half light.   The combination of backlight and silhouette turns one side of Kelek’s face into a shadow, and the other washes out into a tangle of frizzy hair:  almost exactly like the face in <em>Le Guerrier</em>.  It is hard to fathom the cross-dressing:  is it an androgynous image, or a projection of a challenge to male expectations, riffing on Marlene Dietrich, perhaps?  <strong>This is a bizarre masterpiece of moodiness, and as a portrait, we can only marvel at the woman who presented herself in such a stylized, neo-gothic chiascuro.</strong></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Ersatz_cover_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="607"></p><p>It’s fairly obvious where the model for the cover of the book <em>Ersatz</em> came from.   Published in 1981, the book reprints in full color some of the Titres SF cover illustrations, along with other paintings (from <em>Metal Hurlant</em>) that reveal more of a morbid and sado-masochistic sexuality.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF67_Conan_Brigand_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="818"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Nicollet_hurlant_5.jpg" alt="" width="355" height="462"></p><p>Clearly this was a mutual fascination for Nicollet and Keleck, as can be seen in their collaborative works, as well as Keleck’s contributions (as a founding contributor) to the magazine <em>Ah!  Nana</em>, which has been called an early <a href="https://comicsforum.org/2011/09/16/ah-nana-the-forgotten-french-feminist-comics-magazine-by-catriona-macleod/" target="_blank" rel="external">feminist journal</a>.  Produced by women and featuring woman-authored <em>bandes dessinées</em> comics, the first issue described the origin of the magazine:  “Several female artists, colourists and journalists were complaining to each other about having to incorporate male fantasies disguised as essential features of publishing into our work. We decided to act, sketching out the idea of a journal…”   Despite the challenge issues to male fantasies, the topics of magazine covered Cruelty, S&amp;M, Sex and Little Girls, Trans-sexuality,  and Incest.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/AhNana_1.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="655"></p><p>Keleck’s cover for the premier issue of <em>Ah! Nana</em> is not particularly interesting &#8212; showing a man strip dancing in front of raucously amused blue-skinned women &#8212; but the design and details of the painting are nonetheless characteristically Kelleck.  The heavy drapes framing the image, the intense backlight, the cigaret holder, the slightly unfinished faces.</p><p>It is in the <em>Ah! Nana</em> cover that we can begin to pick out the “Keleck-style” when it is the major factor of the collaborative Titres SF covers.  Compare, for example the faces of the blue-skinned women to <em>Ratinox se Venge</em>.  Not only is the skin tone blue-gray, but the features are slightly flattened and stylized.  The face of Angelina looks like a self-portrait of Keleck.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF26b_Ratinox_500px.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="819"></p><p>We might also speculate that self-portrait themes run through the collaborators <em>ouevre.</em>  In <em>Le Rejeton de l’univers</em> (1980), the cover is clearly taken from the infamous photo of Aleister Crowley, but the nose is clearly that of Nicollet himself.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Rejeton_cover_500.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="701"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Jean-Michel-Nicollet_Rejecton.jpeg" alt="" width="427" height="640"></p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>Might we not also surmise that the gypsy woman from the same book is modeled on Keleck?</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/rejecton_gypsy_500.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="737"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Ersatz_keleck_photo.jpg" alt="" width="318" height="492"></p><div style="width: 242px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <a href="https://goo.gl/PTVQMF" target="_blank" rel="external"><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/doisneau_keleck_getty.jpg" alt="(c) Getty Images" width="232" height="340"></a><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    (c) Getty Images<br>  </p><br></div><p>Indeed the cover of <em>Ersatz</em> (1981), (linked above) is pure self-portraiture.   In this case they portray themselves as creepy cold-blooded predators:  are they drinking blood from a tube protruding from the skull of a prone, blue-eyed (possibly alien) victim?   Who knows…</p><p>Another insight into Keleck’s art can be found in her 1984 surrealistic postcard series, a morbid gray and red series of absolute strangeness, bordering on terror.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Keleck_Postcard_surreal2_1984_500.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="703"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Keleck_Postcard_surreal5_1984_500.jpg" alt="" width="1046" height="1478"></p><p>The strange realm of Keleck’s paintings reach their finest polish in the series of children’s books that she illustrated for Editions Hatier (in the late 1980s), including <em>Les Contes de Perrault</em>, <em>Le Magicien D’Oz</em>, <em>Les Frers Grimm</em>.    These paintings deserve their own long treatise, indeed a <a href="http://lectura.fr/expositions/gustavedore/les-contes-de-perrault/le-petit-chaperon-rouge/18/" target="_blank" rel="external">comparison with Gustave Dore</a> can already be found; but let us just marvel at them for now…</p><div style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/BrosGrimm_2_500.jpg" alt="from the Brothers Grimm" width="500" height="717"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    from the Brothers Grimm<br>  </p><br></div><div style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/kelek_mag-d-oz_charlatan_500.jpg" alt="from Wizard of Oz" width="500" height="709"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    from Wizard of Oz<br>  </p><br></div><p>&nbsp;</p><div style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/kelek_chatbotte_500.jpg" alt="from Contes de Perrault" width="500" height="714"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    from Contes de Perrault<br>  </p><br></div><div style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/BrosGrimm_3_500.jpg" alt="from Bros Grimm" width="500" height="726"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    from Bros Grimm<br>  </p><br></div><p>Unfortunately Keleck died in 2003 (age 57), so we cannot ask her more.   Her partner, Nicollet, went on to illustrate many more books, among them a bizarre visit to the Bardo during the day of Keleck’s death, called <em>Apparitions</em>.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/NICOLLET-Apparition-18_417.jpg" alt="" width="417" height="638"></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/apparitions4.jpg" alt="" width="417" height="634"></p><p>Perhaps the life of Keleck will &#8212; and  must &#8212; remain an unfathomable mystery.   After all, her life partner’s tribute to her memory is a <strong>strange grotesquerie about the transmigration of her soul</strong>.   Some trails &#8212; some Fates &#8212; disappear into swirls of smoke, that we need not follow.</p><div style="width: 353px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/ExpoKelek_Ardentes_invitation_card_1985.jpg" alt="Expo Kelek - Ardentes - Invitation card (1985)" width="343" height="342"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    Expo Kelek  -  Ardentes  -  Invitation card (1985)<br>  </p><br></div><div style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF_keleck_androids_500.jpg" alt="Les Androïdes rêvent-ils de moutons électriques?  [Titres SF, No15, 1979]" width="500" height="731"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    Les Androïdes rêvent-ils de moutons électriques? [Titres SF, No15, 1979]<br>  </p><br></div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;My first taste of any artwork associated with Keleck (&lt;em&gt;aka&lt;/em&gt; Kelek), was at Boskone this year, where Andy Gelas brought my attention to two French paperback editions of Conan.   These were &lt;em&gt;Conan Le Guerrier&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Conan Le Cimmerian&lt;/em&gt;, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titres/SF&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;Titres SF editions&lt;/a&gt; from the early 1980s.   Needless to say, the eye-popping contrast in red and black, and the the purity of design in these covers hit me like a sucker-punch in a Philip Marlowe story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF40_Conan_Guerrier_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;809&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/TSF54_Conan_Cimmerian_500px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;827&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Le Cimmerian&lt;/em&gt; has a pure movie-poster effect, with that smashing red background, and the bare skin of the figures has a smooth air-brushed look, while the tightly delineated designs on the metal are all perfectly highlighted.   The first thing I noticed about &lt;em&gt;Le Guerrier&lt;/em&gt; is the darkness of the figure, of the rich draperies, of the stairwell vanishing into shadow.   The hair is certainly done the same way as &lt;em&gt;Le Cimmerian&lt;/em&gt;:  frizzy threads in direct highlight against the background.  But in &lt;em&gt;Le Guerrier&lt;/em&gt;, the eyes, the skin, the deliberate brushstrokes on the wall, and the marble steps; they have a very different aesthetic from the super-slick air-brushing of &lt;em&gt;Le Cimmerian&lt;/em&gt;.  What is going on here?&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="science fiction" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/science-fiction/"/>
    
      <category term="criticism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/criticism/"/>
    
      <category term="artists" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/artists/"/>
    
      <category term="surrealism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/surrealism/"/>
    
      <category term="biography" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/biography/"/>
    
      <category term="France" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/France/"/>
    
      <category term="macabre" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/macabre/"/>
    
      <category term="painting" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/painting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Elephant Man as Reality T.V.</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-elephant-man-as-reality-t-v/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-elephant-man-as-reality-t-v/</id>
    <published>2017-03-11T23:58:17.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A review of  <a href="http://amzn.to/2lO5PnX" target="_blank">The Blind Men and the Elephant</a>   by <a href="http://www.sf-encyclopedia.com/entry/griffin_russell_m" target="_blank">Russell M. Griffin</a></p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/griffin_blind.jpg" alt="" width="316" height="556"></p><p>You would think that a novel investigating the inner life of a freak &#8212; indeed, the freak of freaks: Elephant Man &#8212; would be grim, depressing, and bleak.  You would think that the transformation of one’s body into something hideous and grotesque as a terrible ordeal.  Moreover the psychological pressure of being an actual monster in physical form should be a topic almost unbearable to explore.  And yet, in this novel, <em>The Blind Men and the Elephant</em>, Russell M. Griffin explores all of these difficult ideas and emotions, he pokes them with needles and rubs salt on them over and over again… but strangely enough, he achieves an ethereal, almost philosophical understanding of the subject in the end, and instead of weeping with saccharine sympathy the reader is left pondering moral issues, and laughing bitterly at human weakness.</p><p>It helps that the book is framed as a social commentary and a bitter satire on the hopeless losers of the small town, Butler, Massachusetts.  The protagonist Durwood Leffingwell is a washed up weatherman at a low budget local t.v. station, who smokes dope with the cameraman, and watches with seeming disinterest as his marriage deteriorates.  The cheapness and selfishness of the cast of characters is obvious from the opening lines, evoked with deft jabs and devastating clarity.</p><p>The raw comedy of this book is demonstrated in the first glimpse of Leffingwell’s job, when he is rousted out of bed to answer a phone call from his boss, Trammel, down at the t.v. station:</p><blockquote><p>“I’m trying to cope.  Cope with a little prob we’ve got down on this end.”</p><p>Leffingwell took a deep breath and let go of his day off.  “Shoot.”</p><p>“It’s about our live coverage of the parade today.”</p><p>“Just about to tune in and watch,” Leffingwell lied.</p><p>“You know it’s the biggest thing we’ve done.  We’ve got thousands tied up in telephone line rental and the remote van and the pro switchers from Boston… I mean, Leffingwell, this is a <em><strong>live remote!</strong></em>  This is the <strong><em>big time!</em></strong> This is like ABC doing the Olympics!”  Trammel paused, letting the grandeur of it sink in.  “That’s why I was just sick when I got the call from St. Joe’s just now.”</p><p>“The hospital?  Oberon didn’t slash her wrists again, did she?</p><p>“No, it’s Tanker Hackett.  He’s in traction.”</p><p>“Traction?”</p><p>“They totaled Curt’s VW Rabbit.”</p><p>“Curt too? Is he all right?”</p><p>“Yeah, but his Private Cusp suit’s just a lot of fiberglass tooth crumbs all over Route 111-A.  Leffingwell, Sergeant Smile and Private Cusp were supposed to attract kiddie viewers.  We’ve got no <strong><em>moppet interest</em>.</strong>  WE’RE ABOUT TO SEE THREE THOUSAND DOLLARS GO DOWN THE TUBE!”</p><p>Leffingwell was silent, suspecting where Trammel was headed. Ever since Leffingwell’s promotion to weatherman on the <strong><em>Ten O’Clock News</em></strong>, he’d been supplementing his $97.50 a week take-home by helping out on <strong><em>Sergeant Smile and the Tooth Brigade</em></strong> as the mute end of the many-toothed Mr. Laffy the Horse.</p></blockquote><p>And it all just gets worse from there.   Each line, which seems like a throw-away gag, actually gets tied into the plot during the course of the book.   Griffin manages to escoriate the whole of American society, revealing it’s raw <em>World Weekly News</em>-fed underbelly.</p><p>In the course of the book, Leffingwell gets involved with the Elephant Man, picking up from the freak show pimp who dumped him unceremoniously in Butler, Mass, and plays out his own greed and cynicism against a back-drop of grasping locals, corrupt judges, self-promoting minor poets, and the various phony personalities of the t.v. station.</p><p>There are deep moments of self-reflection from the Elephant Man, who is utterly disconnected with human society, and who painfully reconstructs his past, trying to understand his origins and the meaning for his life on earth.</p><p>The facetious musings of a theologian, and the intrusion of mysterious pursuers <em>wearing sunglasses</em>, point to a horrible truth which is revealed to all eventually.   What makes this novel significant, and not just a slap-stick comedy, is the way in which each of the characters hides and attempts to reconstruct their understanding of what the Elephant Man really is.</p><p>For the theologian, the <em>Virgin birth</em> (which is simultaneously a miracle and an abomination) is too much for his mind to handle and he snaps.  For Leffingwell, the truth becomes a moral question of whether he will continue to hurt and exploit someone who has done him no harm. And for Mother Superior, what good does it do to finally know with certainty that the one child who needed her the most was the one she abandoned?  As she wanders through the wreckage of her life’s work, who was saved?  Was anyone really even helped?</p><p>As for the Elephant Man himself, the truth and catharsis it brings is just another punishment, like Antoine Doinel in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_400_Blows" target="_blank"><em>The 400 Blows</em></a> <strong>he is left walking in the surf and turning around to face the emptiness of a Universe without meaning or mercy</strong>.</p><p>In the Elephant Man’s case, he is not on the beach, but in a parking lot after having been acquitted of a false charge in court.   But his regained freedom is too little and too late to save him from the reality of his own Being.</p><p>Even Leffingwell, who discovers his own compassion too late in the game, only succeeds in raising his protest to the level of being a nuisance to the powers that be.  With his memory erased, and all the knowing parties either dead, missing, or gone mad, there is no epitaph for the Elephant Man’s true nature.</p><p>You’d think all of this is terribly sad, but strangely enough you will spend more time roaring with laughter at this book, then you will stifling back tears.  One drawback, which I should mention, is that the women in the book are generally grasping, selfish, and confused, and seem to randomly focus their affections on men in the story with a sense of pointlessness and low self esteem.   You could fault Griffin on this, and say it is somewhat sexist.  On the other hand, if you look at the whole story, in my view, the male characters are equally self-centered, empty, and blinded by egotism.  I think it is an <strong>equal opportunity</strong> castigation of American society.</p><p>There are moments in the plot where humanity shines through, which is why I would recommend it.  When Leffingwell has mindlessly set up a porno film production involving the Elephant Man as a <em>million dollar idea</em> it is perfectly reflected by the cameraman Stackpole who realizes with disgust what is going on.</p><blockquote><p>“Leff, my man,” said Stackpole, “I just cut myself out.” He handed Leffingwell the massive camera.  “You do anything you want to from here on, but you do it without me.”</p><p>“But why, Stackpole?” Leffingwell said feverishly.</p><p>“<em>Why?</em>  It’s inhuman,” Stackpole said.  “The road back to the human race is through this door.”</p><p>Leffingwell was suddenly alone, the heavy camera tugging at his arm.  His face burned.  He hated himself.</p></blockquote><p>And in these moments of realization, in the midst of wicked satire, this book proves itself worthy of the title.</p><p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/doinel_beach.png" alt="" width="620" height="285"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;A review of  &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2lO5PnX&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Blind Men and the Elephant&lt;/a&gt;   by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sf-encyclopedia
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="social mores" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/social-mores/"/>
    
      <category term="book review" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/book-review/"/>
    
      <category term="horror" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/horror/"/>
    
      <category term="satire" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/satire/"/>
    
      <category term="speculative fiction" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/speculative-fiction/"/>
    
      <category term="television" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/television/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rankled into Action, 2017</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/COSMOS/rankled-into-action-2017/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/COSMOS/rankled-into-action-2017/</id>
    <published>2017-01-03T02:21:39.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone size-medium" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/NoPlanetB_2016_md.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="990"></p><p>Happy New Year to all living beings!   Live long and prosper.</p><p>It’s been a troublesome and unpredictable 2016 &#8212; not that the clump of 365 consecutive days has any particular significance, but since we measure our strangeness in trips around the sun, let’s just say it: 2016 was a bloody pain in the arse.</p><p>Too many good people are gone, and too many rotten ones are left.   The lists of inspiring people who passed away is just too long.  When you think about it, what the hell kind of Universe takes away <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anton_Yelchin" target="_blank" rel="external">Anton Yelchin</a> at age 27, and yet provides a second heart to keep an evil bastard like Dick Cheney going?</p><p>What a seriously messed up agency is responsible for this kind of sadistic continuum?  That is:   if you are going to attribute agency to a Mad Universe.  But what we can observe of our entire cosmos is only an agglomeration of dissipating thermodynamic energy.   On the other hand, if you are an atheist or a pantheist, you need not worry about a Mad or Malevolent Universe.   Lucky day!   Things just are the way they are, and no evil deity is punishing you.   Even luckier for the pantheist, I should say:  <strong>it’s all happening, it’s all real, and it’s all blessed by the Great Spirit.</strong></p><p>Well, count me lucky!   I became a pantheist at some point in the summer haze of the 1960s.   The rocks and stones, the waters flowing, the rushing air that sustains us, that is the good stuff!  We need to work on the sacred water, air, earth; sustainable soils and organic farms forever.</p><p>There really is no Planet B.   Screwing up our planet and running away, like bad campers evacuating a trash-strewn latrine is not an option.   Let’s calm down and focus.   Terra is not a distant dream.  It’s right here and we can save it.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/NoPlanetB_2016_md.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;990&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happ
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="COSMOS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/COSMOS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="ecology" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/ecology/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Victory at Standing Rock</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/victory-at-standing-rock/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/victory-at-standing-rock/</id>
    <published>2016-12-05T20:35:38.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-18T23:57:46.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone size-medium" title="Dave Archambault, Chairman of Standing Rock Reservation" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/DaveArchambault.jpg" width="650" height="390"></p><p>Yesterday we were notified that the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers will not grant the easement to cross Lake Oahe for the Dakota Access pipeline. Instead, they will prepare an Environmental Impact Statement regarding alternative routes for the pipeline. This action strongly vindicates what the Standing Rock Sioux Tribe has been saying all along – that we all have a responsibility to protect our waters for future generations.</p><p>This is an historic moment. For centuries, the Standing Rock Sioux Tribe, and tribes across the country, have faced fundamental injustice at the hands of the federal government  -  which time and again took our lands and tried to destroy our way of life. Our Treaties and our human rights were ignored, our interests in protecting lands and waters were considered unimportant, and our voices were not heard.</p><p>It was this shared history that led Tribes to come together as never before to seek the protection of our waters against the threat of the Dakota Access pipeline. With peace and prayer, indigenous people from hundreds of Tribes said: our future is too important. We can no longer be ignored. <strong>The goal was to protect these sacred waters, and to do so in the name of our children</strong>.</p><p>And, with yesterday’s decision, it is clear that our voices have at long last been heard.</p><p>Yesterday’s decision demonstrates that, despite all the challenges that Tribes face and all of the terrible wrongs the federal government has committed in dealing with us over the years, justice for Indian people still remains possible. My thanks to the Obama Administration, and particularly to Assistant Secretary Darcy, for upholding the law and doing the right thing.</p><p>Yesterday’s decision belongs in large measure to the thousands of courageous people who put their lives on hold to stand with Standing Rock in support of a basic principle &#8212; that water is life. At Standing Rock, our youth played an important role in spreading our message and I am so proud of what they have been able to accomplish.</p><p>But Standing Rock could not have come this far alone. Hundreds of tribes came together in a display of tribal unity not seen in hundreds of years. And many thousands of indigenous people from around the world have prayed with us and made us stronger. I am grateful to each of you. And, as we turn a page with yesterday’s decision, I look forward to working with many of you as you return to your home communities to protect your lands and waters, and the sovereignty of your tribes.</p><p>My thanks to all of our allies, here and around the world, each of whom contributed to this effort. I want to give a special mention to the veterans who have come to Standing Rock in recent days. I am sure that the strength of your message in support of Standing Rock, and the rights of the Water Protectors, had a powerful impact as the Army made its decision. I appreciate all you have done.</p><p>While today is a great day, there is still much that needs to be done to protect Tribal rights and ensure justice for indigenous people everywhere. <strong>Using peace and prayer as our guideposts, and with the teachings of our elders and with inspiration from our youth, I believe there is much we can accomplish for the future.</strong></p><p>Sincerely,</p><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Archambault_II" target="_new">Dave Archambault, II</a>, Chairman</p><p>Standing Rock Sioux Tribe</p><p>[<em>via Standing Rock Action Network, 5 Dec 2016 9:00am  EST</em>]</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-medium&quot; title=&quot;Dave Archambault, Chairman of Standing Rock Reservation&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Dav
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HUMAN BEINGS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/HUMAN-BEINGS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="ecology" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/ecology/"/>
    
      <category term="justice" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/justice/"/>
    
      <category term="protest" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/protest/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Placing Names:  it is a thing!</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/placing-names-it-is-a-thing/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/placing-names-it-is-a-thing/</id>
    <published>2016-09-07T03:36:10.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/placing_names.jpg" target="_blank" rel="external"><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/placing_names_sm.jpg" alt=""></a></p><p>Well, about three years and a field of poppies later, the combined efforts of a zillion scholars have arrived on my desk in a physical manifestation of printed paper, green bindings, and a snappy little dark red trident logo! <strong>_<a href="http://www.iupress.indiana.edu/product_info.php?products_id=808056" target="_blank">Placing Names</a>_ is a thing!</strong> They actually printed it and sent it to all us editors and authors.</p><p>Pretty neat.</p><p>Who would have imagined the backwater field of historical toponyms would find newfound relevance in a world of interconnected data?  But then again, since many things of significance are named, and since they exist in both time and three-dimensional space, changing form as they ramble across hill and dale…</p><p><strong>why shouldn’t the logic of tracing the history of place names serve as a template for understanding the mystery</strong> of these transmutations?</p><p>How many other antiquarian, fuss-budget compilations of old named things tried to tackle the thorny logic of temporal, geographic, and semantic attributes that all change independently, and have a variable number of relationships?   Sure, why not?</p><p>Let’s celebrate the launch of this strange tome, and raise a glass to the pirates who sailed the seven seas!</p><blockquote><p><em>Fifteen men on dead man’s chest</em></p><p><em>yo ho ho, and a bottle of rum</em></p><p><em>drink and the devil be done for the rest</em></p><p><em>yo ho ho, and a bottle of rum!</em></p></blockquote><p>Many thanks to my co-editors and co-authors.  And be sure to rush out and <a href="http://www.iupress.indiana.edu/product_info.php?products_id=808056" target="_blank">buy a copy right now</a>!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/placing_names.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/placing_
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gazetteer" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/gazetteer/"/>
    
      <category term="historical geography" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/historical-geography/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Green Chili Jones:  Solved</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/green-chili-jones-solved/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/green-chili-jones-solved/</id>
    <published>2016-08-27T04:38:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So what is it with New Mexico green chilis? Is it something in the soil? <strong>Something in the dusty valleys scorched by the desert sun where even lizards fear to crawl and only the toughest, gnarliest lifeforms can eke out an existence, raving into the blue-black sky with a fierce scream of defiance:  <em>Universe, que haces, Universe!</em></strong></p><p>Sure, there is a lightness of being under the enchanted sky, and a fatalistic attitude of total abandon, defiance, and belligerence that makes New Mexico what it is. That spirit thrives in those green chilis. They are like the super-energy pills eaten by Underdog, no kidding.</p><p>Now most people on the East coast can get their chilis in a jar, or a can, or flash-frozen and flown to them by next day Fedex… but normal home-grown New Mexicans are a sort of funky gang.  We just want a paper bag of chilis with the stems on so that we can roast and peel ‘em at home.  We even watch the local news (KOAT-TV) to see what is going on in the big city &#8212; Albuquerque &#8212; and it’s daily batch of grisly murders, head-on car wrecks, drug-crazed robberies, car chases, shoot-outs, and the occasional “human-interest” story: you know, like a retired firefighter giving some pre-schoolers karate lessons, or some shit like that.</p><p>Thus, it should come as no surprise to you, dear reader, that I <strong>already KNEW</strong> the green chili season was early this year! There was a <a href="http://www.koat.com/news/green-chile-harvest-begins-early/40869350" target="_blank" rel="external">report in July</a> that chilis were almost ready to harvest, so I had my eyes peeled!</p><p>Sure enough Sophia and I spotted a few bins of the gorgeous Hatch green chilis last weekend at Whole Foods. We snapped up about half of them, which turned out to be eight pounds. Eight gorgeous pounds of fresh green chilis straight off the truck from Nuevo Mexico. <em>What could be better?</em></p><p>We washed them and started lining them up on roasting pans:</p><div class="figure"><br>  <p><br>    <img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/hatch_2016_1.jpg" alt="fresh chilis ready to roast"><br>  </p><br><br>  <p class="caption"><br>    fresh chilis ready to roast<br>  </p><br></div><p>After charring the skins in the broiler, we tossed them to cool in a bowl.</p><div class="figure"><br>  <p><br>    <img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/hatch_2016_2.jpg" alt="nicely charred"><br>  </p><br><br>  <p class="caption"><br>    nicely charred<br>  </p><br></div><p>Then we start lining them up on a cutting board, just to look at em all before wrapping them.</p><div class="figure"><br>  <p><br>    <img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/hatch_2016_3.jpg" alt=""><br>  </p><br></div><p>Once they are cooled off, we double wrap piles of six chilis in plastic wrap bundles.</p><div class="figure"><br>  <img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/hatch_2016_4.jpg" alt=""><br></div><p>They can be frozen, and after thawing and peeling off the skins, cooked up in meal sized batches any time!</p><p>The first batch was so chewy and fresh! I had about 1/6 of the batch left over and was able to make a New Mexico style <strong>wet</strong> burrito after getting one to take out from <a href="http://www.victoriataqueria.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">La Victoria taqueria</a>.</p><p>This is the life!</p><div class="figure"><br>  <img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/hatch_2016_5.jpg" alt="nicely charred"><br></div>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;So what is it with New Mexico green chilis? Is it something in the soil? &lt;strong&gt;Something in the dusty valleys scorched by the desert su
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Albuquerque" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/Albuquerque/"/>
    
      <category term="green chili" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/green-chili/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fallout from Quincy Adams:  Readercon 2016</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/fallout-from-quincy-adams-readercon-2016/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/fallout-from-quincy-adams-readercon-2016/</id>
    <published>2016-08-07T21:28:54.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/monkey.jpg" alt=""></p><p>It’s strange to think about the fun-fest of Readercon &#8212; <em>which it always turns out to be</em> &#8212; as a hotbed of controversy where ripples of fallout will radiate outward for weeks and months after the event. On the other hand, science fiction fandom is a sort of canary in the coal mine of society at large. The feuds and alignments and banishments and <em>rapprochements</em> that swirl around fandom, punctuated by mass scrimmage events (also known as cons), are now inextricably linked to the culture wars raging around us.</p><p>It wasn’t always this way. Long ago, in never never land, cons were communal freak-outs held by like-minded escapists as a sort of exhibitionist rebellion against the bleakness of <em>mundane</em> culture. A con was where your propellor beanie, flowing cape, Vulcan ears, and purple velvet bag-of-holding concealing a pint of scumble were <em>perfectly normal</em>, and you were surrounded by fellow fen celebrating the freedom to be weird.</p><a id="more"></a><p>Not that this spirit of letting our freak flag fly has changed all that much, but what has changed is the sense that certain values, certain codes of conduct, and the moral obligation to <em>represent</em> people of color, women, Moslems, GLBT, or any group that has been under-represented until now is no longer an option.</p><p>It is this feeling of political correctness acting as a form of coercion that has become a lightning rod in recent years. Personally, I can commiserate with anyone who feels oppressed and alienated in this crazy consumerist society we live in. <strong>I think tearing down the patriarchy is a good thing: and I would like to tear down Wall Street, the military intelligence complex, industrialized farming, and big Pharma while we are at it!</strong></p><p>The more panels we have on Afro-futurism, women writers, alternate cultures, and tree frogs the better! (Disclosure: I also like tree frogs.)</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/201608_frog.jpg" alt=""></p><p>What I hope we can avoid is to shed the old <em>normalized</em> social forms of oligarchy and privelege and exchange them for a new vanguard of behavioural gate-keepers who are going to dictate to us what is the <em>new</em> norm. That could be dangerous.</p><p>The impression that this has already taken place is the <em>raison d’être</em> of the so-called Rabid Puppies. They seem to think that a secret cabal of SJWs is pulling the strings of fandom, loading the Hugo slates with works by women and minorities, in a way that is <em>unfair</em> and disenfranchises <em>them</em>, whoever <em>they</em> are. <strong>This theory is, to say the least: totally fucking crazy.</strong></p><p>Just to promote the books you think are deserving of recognition does not enlist you into a secret cabal. By contrast, to promote a particular slate of works and recruit as many people as possible to vote for exactly the same slate is to form a <em>public</em> cabal. If the intention is to disrupt the nomination process of the Hugo awards, then this <em>is</em> a form of conspiracy. It is a group of people deliberately <em>conspiring</em> to bombard a public process with monkey-wrenches. Yes, there are some wild monkeys who throw shit at everyone and scream. People who emulate this behaviour should not be the ones to decide how others behave. Did these people not get the memo?</p><p>Consequently, the recriminations and accusations that resulted from this whole debacle tends to make con-runners and SMOFs more defensive and more rule-oriented than they were in the past. Of necessity cons must remain open and inclusionary. Every type of fan should be welcome and feel safe among their fellow fen. On the other hand, this requires some rules and boundaries to be set. We can no longer assume that unwritten codes of <em>common decency</em> are effective, and therefore things have to be written down. And this, of course, just seems to reinforce the paranoid notion that there are some SJWs hiding out on secret committees to enforce their concept of appropriateness.</p><p>What a mess. From my humble rock on the bottom of the pond it seems like the crazies have poisoned the well. They came screaming out their echo chamber to sabotage the commons. I feel like I am in one of David Bunch’s <em>Moderan</em> stories. The <em>uber</em>-paranoid attack dogs have gotten off their leash. Who the hell knows what will happen next.</p><p>But this is not what actually happened at Readercon 2016. What actually happened is that the con moved from the bucolic green sward of Burlington to the (pardon my French) <em>ass</em>-end of Quincy. Many people were happy with the new hotel and location. I thought it was a miserable nightmare, perched on an outcrop of rock and cement overlooking bleak highways, and at the very end of a long, steep, searingly ugly driveway untrodden by human beings. William Hope Hodgson might have liked this spot, as a model for the gateway to a dimension of terror. But I didn’t find very nice.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/201608_qadams_sm.jpg" alt=""></p><p>Okay, I am being bitchy. Maybe for people who only drive in those apocalypse-inducing internal combustion bombs the Quincy Marriott is fine. But for me, riding public transit, it was hell. Two solid hours it took for me to get from Alewife to Quincy Adams.</p><p>A full month has passed, and I am still a bit queasy from the mess that the T made of my trips to Readercon this year. Okay, it is not <em>entirely</em> Readercon’s fault. The repair work that forced a bus connection from Kendall to Park is not supposed to be permanent: but it should have been predictable! And the same goes for the fact that trains simply DO NOT run beyond JFK on the weekends. Typical waiting times at JFK are 20 minutes, so if you are switching from an Ashmont train to a Braintree train you are just <strong>shit out of luck.</strong> This is all something that Readercon must have known.</p><p>Gripe-fest concluded, the con itself was pretty damn fun, as usual. Except for the grief that we all felt for losing David Hartwell &#8212; <em>his framed photo and tie standing in mute tribute in the Dealer Room</em> &#8212; everyone I met was in a fine mood.</p><p>From the New Paltz writer who had <em>gafiated</em> for two decades, to the regulars like George Morgan, Mark Borok, Diane Weinstein, Ed Koenig, Frank Wu, Neil Clarke and so on… it was an amazingly fun time.</p><p>One faanish highlight were a my conversations with Jean Berman, who was <a href="https://alexshvartsman.com/2015/07/13/john-h-costello-documents/" title="John H. Costello" target="_blank" rel="external">John H. Costello’s</a> partner for many years. Last year, she was largely responsible for making his <a href="http://yunchtime.net/?p=1799" target="_blank" rel="external">entire book collection</a> available for free, and several boxes remaining from that huge stash were still visible on this year’s freebie tables.</p><p>I bought my usual stack of goodies in the Dealer Room, and had a terrific time talking to Neil Clarke, Jean Gonzalez, and various people wandering around the tables.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/201608_readercon.jpg" alt=""></p><p>On Friday, July 8th, there were a preponderance of panels on Dystopia and Apocalypse… do we wonder why? In the mundane <em>real world</em> we have an actual proto-fascist running as the nominee for POTUS. Let us retreat into our world of “cozy dystopias” and hide!</p><p>But of course, the coziness is not all fun and games. Looking at Harry Potter’s school, Hogwarts, as an example, the panelists of <em>Cozy Dystopias</em> were quick to point out that extra-judicial killings and soul-suckings that take place at the talons of evil Dementors are not <strong><em>exactly</em></strong> cozy.</p><p>The Ministry of Magic also functions as an oppressive government &#8212; with no transparency &#8212; and is utterly restricted and elitist. Many of the main characters and their family members, though they benefit from their appointments or relationships with the Ministry, are also subject to it’s capricious decisions, and often have no idea what is going on. Indeed, it was only the <em>mud-blood</em>, Hermione, as an outsider to the elitist system of social mobility, who establishes the House of Rights. Being outside, Hermione can bear witness the injustices that are otherwise ignored.  And why is it Hermione, not Harry, who becomes an activist?  She’s smarter than him, for one thing.</p><p>In a session called <em>Author Trademark or Personal Cliché</em> the panelists explored the writing of various authors, looking for particularities that represent their individual styles. Are these traits in an author’s work intentional or subconscious? Gillian Daniels said that “Writing is like presenting a view of yourself in the mirror that you don’t want to show anyone; but you do anyway!”</p><p>How to get inside the head of a writer and know what they were thinking? Trying to grasp another writer’s obsession: that would be an interesting challenge, the panelists agreed.</p><p>I missed the panel <em>Integrating the Id</em>, which apparently explored all manner of sexuality. But a choice quote from <strong>Chip Delany made it to the twitter-verse: “Be ready for someone to tell you: &#8216;I am sorry. The last time <em>I</em> had sex with a camel, it was nothing like that.’ </strong>“</p><p>On Saturday morning, there was a lack-luster panel called <em>Sorting Taxonomies</em>, which had great panelists &#8212; including Peter Straub and Greer Gilman &#8212; but was often constrained by the narrow questions from the moderator, Nepveau. She wanted the panelists to rattle off a bullet list of characteristics that define <em>genre</em>, but the panelists contrarily went off on their own tangents, speculating on what constitutes the voice and vision of certain authors.</p><p>Gilman said that it is not so much a set of traits that attracts her to a certain type of writing, but rather the <strong>“details of what the author is filtering out of the Universe for me to notice: a drowned arm… with bracelets! Walking out to look for the evening star… then the Evening Star comes to life and becomes a character!”</strong></p><p>It was nonetheless interesting to watch Straub, snapping his neck around suddenly, to peer at someone with awesome intensity; or to watch Gilman, as she stares up to the sky while speaking in general (usually poetic) terms, then looks down at others when making a point.</p><div><br>  <pre><code class="language-none"> Overheard in the con-suite, first fandom’s David Kyle was talking<br> about an astronaut returning to Earth who picks up radio signals<br> that were originally broadcast decades earlier from stations<br> and transmitters that no longer exist.  “It’s quite possible,”<br> Kyle speculated, “that certain kinds of radiation or vibrations<br> exist that can last forever.  They might go on echoing through<br> the Universe for all eternity.”</code></pre><br></div><p>While attending the <em>Sorting Taxonomies</em> panel, I managed to miss <em>Beyond Strong Female Characters</em>, which seems to have generated the most controversy this year. In a session described as a <em>shit-show</em>, the moderator managed to insult the only African American woman on the panel, Mikki Kendall. <a href="https://mikkikendall.com/2016/07/13/readercon-low-point-lessons/" target="_blank" rel="external">Kendall’s reaction</a> seemed measured, while <a href="https://sabrinavourvoulias.com/2016/07/11/readercon-27-confronting-the-fails/" target="_blank" rel="external">others responded</a> with more anger at the situation. This reached a boiling point with a <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=from%3A%40anerdcalledrage%20AND%20%23readercon&amp;src=typd" target="_blank" rel="external">blogger</a> who expresses volcanic eruptions of anger with hair-trigger sensitivity.</p><p>Sure, it is fine to be angry, and never to back down on issues of racism, sexism, bigotry, and injustice. I am 100% down with that, and support the need for action. But, call me whatever you want, (<em>I’m not trying to be the tone-police, here</em>), I just find it counter-productive to constantly be attacking and insulting everyone who you don’t approve of.   Somebody with the track record of Vox needs to be cut down to size, but I don’t really perceive Ellen Kushner as the enemy.   Sounds like she was being snobby and bitchy.  There has got to be a better way to carry this conversation forward and improve our society. In truth, I think Mikki Kendall and Ellen Kushner working this out in public is the best thing that can happen, and I hope it leads to more interesting and better integrated, more open and less hostile discussions all over the place.</p><p>Another bit of flak erupted in the <strong><em>Blue Collar SF</em> panel, which surprised me mostly by managing NOT to mention labor history, socialism, the Wobblies, or anything else very political.</strong>  Bud Sparhawk spent a lot of time talking about his own stories that featured working class characters, including one case where the machinists working on some sort of space-tech had to take matters into their own hands because the designs provided to them by a huge team of designers and engineers had flaws when it came time to actually assemble the stuff.  The moderator, Allen Steele remarked: <em>“too many chiefs, not enough injuns.”</em>  This comment was careless, in poor taste, even insulting to Native Americans.  No doubt about that.  According to one reviewer, the statement caused several in the audience to get up and leave, but she stayed on <em>because it’s hard to look away from an accident,”</em> and she hope that <em>“clueless leaders will experience a corrective from their co-panelists.”</em></p><p>But on the other hand, I was there, and I specifically heard Sparhawk’s story that prompted the comment. It was a poor choice of words, yeah; but later I saw a posts on twitter questioning why Steele was even on the panel in the first place and insinuating that he was a racist.  Well, it’s pretty clear that Steele writes near-future SF about working class characters… that was why he was on the <em>Blue Collar SF</em> panel. And he did write a novel with a Native American protagonist, <em>Clarke County Space.</em>  Though some people have dumped on his “Colonialist” <em>Coyote</em> series, I think Steele has done a fairly decent job of writing about people from different races and backgrounds in his books.</p><p><strong>Do I wish there were more Native American SF writers, and more SF books featuring Native Americans? Hell yes!</strong>  I’m a big fan of G. C. Edmondson’s <em>Chapayeca (aka Blue Face)</em>, for one example.   As for Steele’s character, Detective John Bighorn, he is not perfect, but he doesn’t come across as a cliché, or seem quite the noble savage template of Andre Norton’s <em>Beastmaster</em>.   My reading of Steele gives me the impression that his intentions are good, whereas I’m not sure if I would cut the same slack to the cultural appropriation in J. K. Rowling’s Native American wizard “history”.</p><p>In sum, <strong>I just think that we can be prickly, we can call each other out, but we can also smoke a peace pipe and build a better society to live in! Let’s get on to that constructive part, because the real racists, bigots, and right-wing reactionaries would absolutely LOVE to see us divided and squabbling forever…</strong> If we go on that way, Vox and his friends will be cackling like vultures on their Saguaro cacti.</p><p>We’re science fiction faans. We started all this shit: fandom, zines, cons, sub-cultures, ultra-networked self-reflective agents of social change. We can do this. This is our community mission, and we are shit out of time, with no room for failure. We’ve got this.</p><p>On a lighter note, it was terrific to attend the GOH Interview with Tim Powers, conducted by Gary K. Wolfe. Though I am a huge Powers fan, my main reason for this is his novel <em>Anubis Gates</em>. There were a few other books of his that I couldn’t quite get through. But after hearing this lively interview, I’ve definitely rekindled my interest.</p><p>For instance, Powers said <strong>“when it comes to ouija boards, tarot, and the like, I think it’s all nonsense. I don’t believe ANY of it. But, I’m scared of it!”</strong></p><p>And “writing within the bounds of actual historical events is like working within the lines of a tennis court to play a match. What I do, is not to reconstruct the entire historical narrative… I just look for cool things to pluck out, and then I string them together.”</p><p><em>Ah, that explains it!</em></p><p>“You approach the research of historical facts with an honorary paranoid-schizophrenic squint: did you know that Edison’s last breath was caught in a test tube with a cork! Really, it’s in Dearborn, Michigan, in the Edison museum. So when History just gives you details like this &#8212; and it ALWAYS DOES &#8212; you just go with them.”</p><p>“To draw the reader into the supernatural story, you seed in references to the real world… That sonnet. Those cave paintings. Did you know that the body of the poet Shelley, having been drowned, was found with his face and hands eaten by fish. Yeah, RIGHT! By fish! This stuff just writes itself.”</p><p><strong>Since we all have that primordial part of the brain that lights up in terror, I say: let’s light that up!”</strong></p><p>Inspired by Powers anecdotes, I then bought copies of <em>Declare</em> and John Berlyne’s <em>Tim Powers Secret Histories</em> which is just a mammoth Bibliography of Powers’ works. The Berlyne book also has an essay on <em>Anubis Gates</em> by China Mieville, which is worth the price of admission.</p><p>“<em>Anubis Gates</em> is a carnavelesque of amazing generosity. <strong>It revels in its magicians, its historical conspiracies, its beggar-princes, its identityless brawling poets, its philosophizing monsters, its eggshell-sailors, its cross-dressing investigators, its quasi-werewolf body-jumping serial killers.</strong> Among other things.”</p><p>Indeed!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/monkey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s strange to think about the fun-fest of Readercon &amp;#8212; &lt;em&gt;which it always turns out to be&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; as a hotbed of controversy where ripples of fallout will radiate outward for weeks and months after the event. On the other hand, science fiction fandom is a sort of canary in the coal mine of society at large. The feuds and alignments and banishments and &lt;em&gt;rapprochements&lt;/em&gt; that swirl around fandom, punctuated by mass scrimmage events (also known as cons), are now inextricably linked to the culture wars raging around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t always this way. Long ago, in never never land, cons were communal freak-outs held by like-minded escapists as a sort of exhibitionist rebellion against the bleakness of &lt;em&gt;mundane&lt;/em&gt; culture. A con was where your propellor beanie, flowing cape, Vulcan ears, and purple velvet bag-of-holding concealing a pint of scumble were &lt;em&gt;perfectly normal&lt;/em&gt;, and you were surrounded by fellow fen celebrating the freedom to be weird.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="con report" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/con-report/"/>
    
      <category term="readercon" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/readercon/"/>
    
      <category term="controversy" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/controversy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Redemption Song</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/redemption-song/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/redemption-song/</id>
    <published>2016-07-21T07:40:57.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div style="width: 590px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/AndrejsPeregudovs_TaiwanRobbery_sm_Jul2016.jpg" alt="" width="580" height="1031"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    Andreis Peregudovs being led to find the stolen stash of money.<br>  </p><br></div><p>Pondering the depths of guilt and despair, the criminal is led to the scene of a crime.  His handlers are not brutal, they too are subdued; as if ashamed themselves, and feeling the general shame of a greedy act.  Well, it was a robbery &#8212; which is wrong &#8212; but it was not murder or assault or physically violent.  It was an intellectual job, a computerized heist, involving hackers and exploits that emptied the contents of ATM machines into the hands of a well-organized gang.   The thieves, apparently, had been active for some time.  Wreaking their computerized havoc on the banks of Europe and America almost with impunity, they suddenly fell into a trap on the yam-shaped island.</p><p>And now, one of the ring-leaders, being led in handcuffs and muddy slippers down the rain-streaked hillside, bows his head.  He looks penitent.   He had asked his captors if there was a possibility of the death penalty.  His white plastic rain poncho is framed by the dripping yellow ponchos of the unarmed policemen, as they try not to slip on the steep muddy path.   Somewhere along the trail, a filthy old duffel bag, bursting with stacks of 100 NT$ bills, awaited them.</p><p>This scene, at once so droll and unrehearsed, captured in the midst of the investigation process, has a strangely beautiful, glowing, transcendence to it.   For some reason, when I saw the form of the suspect, hands bound, his long sinewy body twisting slightly and lost in deep meditation on his own sins, I suddenly thought of the paintings of El Greco.   Those giant lush canvases, full of figures interacting in various angular poses, which decompose into brightly contrasting zones of color, are imbued with El Greco’s heavy Catholocism, and scenes of melancholy; like <em>The Disrobing of Christ</em>.</p><div style="width: 590px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><br>  <img class="" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/El_Expolio,_por_El_Greco.jpg" alt="" width="580" height="997"><br><br>  <p class="wp-caption-text"><br>    The Disrobing of Christ, El Greco (1579)<br>  </p><br></div><p>What an odd thought, really.   It is not that I sympathize with the criminal so much as respect the care and sense of calm which the police have in dealing with the matter.  All of this captured in the lens and splashed in a vertical composition of slow and moody actions built out of rich flat color shapes.   This is a great photo.  If nothing else, it brings me to the rainy and muddy steps in the forest where the bag of money was dumped.   It puts me exactly into the scene, and into the mood.  How will it end?   In some sordid courtroom anti-climax.  Sure.  Doesn’t it always?</p><p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;div style=&quot;width: 590px&quot; class=&quot;wp-caption alignnone&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;img class=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/AndrejsPeregudovs_TaiwanRobber
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HUMAN BEINGS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/HUMAN-BEINGS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="crime" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/crime/"/>
    
      <category term="life imitating art" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/life-imitating-art/"/>
    
      <category term="redemption" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/redemption/"/>
    
      <category term="Taiwan" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/Taiwan/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>It&#39;s Towel Day:  Let your freak flag fly!</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/its-towel-day-let-your-freak-flag-fly/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/its-towel-day-let-your-freak-flag-fly/</id>
    <published>2016-05-25T20:50:41.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T01:25:06.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/towel_day_sm.jpg" alt="" width="451" height="461"></p><p>Yes, it’s <a href="http://towelday.org/" target="_blank" rel="external">towel day</a>!   And I wore my official <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miffy" target="_blank" rel="external">Miffy</a> towel, that I bought at Watsons on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nathan_Road" target="_blank" rel="external">Nathan Road</a> in Tsim Sha Tsui, Hong Kong many years ago.   It’s a little thread-bare, but <strong>when you are roughing it across the galaxy, struggling to survive against merciless hordes of alien creatures, it’s good to have a farcical bunny on your side!</strong></p><p>As I walked across Harvard Yard, letting my freak flag fly proudly in the morning breeze, I may have been a little out of tune with the milling crowds of alumni and graduates in their black robes and crimson purple scarves.   Sure, they will celebrate their commencement tomorrow, and go on to take up their places as the elite rulers of the world… but I am celebrating the life of <a href="http://www.douglasadams.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Douglas Adams</a>! &#8212; that great surrealist and comedic philosopher &#8212; and this old Miffy towel is a good enough symbol for me.</p><p>Aloha, compadres!  Don’t panic.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/towel_day_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;451&quot; height=&quot;461&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it’s &lt;a href=&quot;ht
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HUMAN BEINGS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/HUMAN-BEINGS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="science fiction" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/science-fiction/"/>
    
      <category term="hitchhiking" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/hitchhiking/"/>
    
      <category term="memorials" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/memorials/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Agit-prop 2016:  Democratic Socialism Wants You</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/IDEAS/agit-prop-2016-democratic-socialism-wants-you/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/IDEAS/agit-prop-2016-democratic-socialism-wants-you/</id>
    <published>2016-05-21T20:15:08.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HideYaKids_poster_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="693"></p><p>Just before the New York primary I noticed this sign posted on the Quincy Street billboard in Harvard Yard.   This is directly across the street from entrance to the Harvard Art Museum, at the gate between Philosophy, Robinson and Sever Halls.   It is a fairly good traffic spot in the mornings.</p><p>Whoever posted this has my kudos!   It’s actually a pretty funny mash-up of the “Hide ya kids, hide yo wife” meme with the idiotic fear-mongering that has been going on about Bernie Sanders and the menace of “democratic socialism.”   Making use of an old-fashioned image of the iconic Russian bear attacking and slavering on top of prone Uncle Sam is rather ridiculous…  Bernie’s political life and positions have nothing to do with Russia or with Russia’s state planned socialism.   Indeed, <strong>if Americans had any sense of reality whatsoever, they would realize that entire purpose of our Federal government and its institutions is socialist in nature. </strong>  Assuming democracy actually exists here in the USA &#8212; which is seriously in doubt after the recent debacle in Las Vegas has revealed &#8212; then it is most certainly democratic socialism to begin with.   Really, we could only be so lucky as to adopt the policies discussed by Michael Moore in <a href="http://wheretoinvadenext.com/" target="_blank">Where to Invade Next</a>, and be slightly more in tune with the times in order to enjoy the advantages that democratic social policies provide.</p><p>Of course, the “Wants You” slogan predicates the idea that this strange and monstrous thing &#8212; this <em>democratic socialism</em> thing &#8212; is simultaneously going to destroy your peace and security (thus Hide Ya Kids, Hide Ya Wife), and  at the same time recruit you to join it.   How insidious!   <strong>The thing you fear will propagandize you into joining it.</strong>   Pretty amusing!   This is clearly a fun bit of agit-prop, deliberately messing with our “normal” brainwashing program, that is beamed at us 24 hours a day.   Thanks for that chuckle, hermano!   And I liked the silk-screening too.   More of this!</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HideYaKids_poster_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;520&quot; height=&quot;693&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just before t
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="IDEAS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/IDEAS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="memes" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/memes/"/>
    
      <category term="politics" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/politics/"/>
    
      <category term="agit-prop" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/agit-prop/"/>
    
      <category term="socialism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/socialism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Sleek and Memorable Art of A. J. Donnell</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-sleek-and-memorable-art-of-a-j-donnell/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/the-sleek-and-memorable-art-of-a-j-donnell/</id>
    <published>2016-05-14T21:52:05.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In another post (about <a href="http://yunchtime.net/?p=1826" target="_blank" rel="external">blood moons and werewolves</a>) I had occasion to examine the various cover paintings for Jack Williamson’s great novel, <em>Darker Than You Think</em>.   In addition to Edd Cartier’s black and white illustration, Jeff Jones’ transmogrification of tigers and snakes, and David G. Klein’s rather literalist take on the eros and violence in the book, I was strangely charmed by the cover painting done by A. J. Donnell.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/DonnellAJ_DarkerThanYouThink_1948_sm.jpg" alt="" width="338" height="381"></p><p>Who was A. J. Donnell, I wondered?</p><p>It turns out that I couldn’t dig up much info on him.   Andrew Julian Donnell seems to have served as a Staff Sergeant in WWII, according to the <a href="http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&GSln=donnell&GSiman=1&GScid=109411&GRid=36240388&" target="_blank">gravestone</a> in Fort Scott, Bourbon County, Kansas, which gives his dates as 1905 to 1991.   The <a href="http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/ea.cgi?25822" target="_blank">ISFDB</a> indicates that he was born in Kansas City, about 90 miles north of where he was buried.    After his stint in WWII, A. J. Donnell was living in Reading, Pennsylvania, where he was an artist working for the Glidden Paint Company.   According to Lloyd Arthur Esbach’s account of how he founded the Fantasy Press, Donnell was one of the first four investors, who teamed up to put in $500 each in order to launch the company.</p><p><span style="font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif;">As Esbach tells it, he was kicking the idea around with his co-worker, G. H. MacGregor, who said:  “We could get Donnell here”—the artist who was in the room at the time—“and he could do the illustrating. Maybe add Leman Houck—he’s a bookkeeper—and with each of us putting in five hundred we’d be on our way.”    (see “The Fantasy Press Story”  published in <a href="http://pdf.textfiles.com/efanzines/EK/eI27/index.htm#fp" target="_blank">Earl Kemp’s eI27, Aug 2006</a>)<br> </span></p><p>But hardly anything else is known about the artist.</p><p>The Science Fiction Encyclopedia provides a thoughtful reflection on his art.</p><blockquote><p>Donnell’s covers tended to emphasize simply drawn designs, but these often seemed perfectly appropriate for the material; his stark, sometimes monochromatic renderings of spacecraft for the covers for Smith’s Space Operas, for example, capture the unpolished energy of this work much better than later, more sophisticated artwork. Also, although Robert Weinberg reports that Donnell had little attachment to sf, he apparently read the books he illustrated with unusual care, as indicated by his cover for Heinlein’s _<a href="http://66.media.tumblr.com/829286b21105cc4d4a36d341e8dd6083/tumblr_o76htcLTV21qgxv6vo1_500.jpg" target="_blank">Beyond This Horizon</a><em>, since its image of a boy playing with sand inside an hourglass perfectly captures the novel’s central theme:  a long effort to craft a superior human being through generations of careful breeding. Similarly, his arresting cover for Stanley G Weinbaum’s </em><a href="http://www.lawrenceperson.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Martian-Odyssey.jpeg" target="_blank">A Martian Odyssey and Others</a>_, showing a masked Egyptian bowing toward a birdlike Martian, cleverly illustrates Donnell’s awareness of the theory expressed in Weinbaum’s “Valley of Dreams”,  that Martians like his Tweel had visited ancient Egypt to be received as gods.</p><p>(see <a href="http://www.sf-encyclopedia.com/entry/donnell_a_j" target="_blank">SFE A. J. Donnell</a>)</p></blockquote><p>Robert Weinberg, in his Biographical Dictionary comments that Donnell was the staff artist for <em>The Whilhelm Ambassador</em>, whatever that was.   I found a 1939 copyright entry for a periodical called “Wilhelm ambassador,” so I suppose that was it.   But, apparently whatever Donnell created for that publication is long forgotten.</p><p>Not the case for his science fiction art, which is sleek, polished, and memorable.   If the cover for Stanley Weinbaum’s <em>The Black Flame</em> doesn’t knock your socks off, then I can’t help you!</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://65.media.tumblr.com/55d47c2d8f6042773c15b4f822b7aad2/tumblr_o76i94CWqx1qgxv6vo1_500.jpg" alt="" width="499" height="750"></p><p>Since Donnell was both the art director and illustrator for the early Fantasy Press covers, he was designing the covers, lettering them, and probably setting up the color separations as well.   His simple and yet effective use of the cover designs &#8212; in this case with red letters floating over a woman’s towering (and sparkling!) coiffure &#8212;   is typically something that would have artist and art director strangling each other over an office desk.  But here, on the soft green background, it just works!</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://65.media.tumblr.com/69920465e910f94d10e5634e2399ef1a/tumblr_o76i1siGoU1qgxv6vo1_500.jpg" alt="" width="480" height="750"></p><p>You can see where he was going with the original illustration, contrasting the soft gradient of the skin tones that had a hint of warmth, against the vivid strokes of black india ink swirling through the woman’s hair.   Adding the sparkling white stars to soften the crisp lines, also showed off Donnell’s technical skill as an illustrator.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://66.media.tumblr.com/6893a9c18f4cb990ba20bb2a89fdd041/tumblr_o76hy5GCw01qgxv6vo1_500.jpg" alt="" width="480" height="539"></p><p>The ravages of war in space are neatly depicted in Donnell’s painting for <em>Triplanetary</em>, first book in Doc Smith’s Lensman series.    Here the use of airbrush, oil, and hand-painted lettering is simply fantastic.  The smooth cylinders of the spaceships are tumbling through the sky like so many compressed air tanks, some of them bursting into flames or burnt into useless chunks of smoldering metal.   This band of destruction is emanating from a mandala-like shape hanging in the sky &#8212; apparently the Nevians spaceship unleashing their death ray that melts all it touches into an allotropic iron plasma.  There is an exceptional subtlety in the way Donnell has used a simple, blurry geometric shape to represent the superior alien race.</p><p>Once again, the boldness with which Donnell framed the colorless death ray against a bright blue sky, and the way he slashed across the action with a boldly outlined red title demonstrates what an artist is willing to do when focused on the the impact of the complete design, rather than just the painting.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://67.media.tumblr.com/411e04e761a4678c6245376aab35c60c/tumblr_o76hwiHlKy1qgxv6vo1_500.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="540"></p><p>Another curiosity, is Donnell’s unused cover design for <em>First Lensman</em>.   In this cover, the lens &#8212; <strong>a device that super-amplifies the mental powers of the wearer</strong> &#8212; looks like a fancy wristwatch, with a luxurious band.  The anonymous face, floating in space behind the lens, and the trickles of stars floating around it look more like bubbles in water than stars.  Clearly this design was not going to make for a stunning cover.   The lettering was pretty neat, though!</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://67.media.tumblr.com/7e21f1240639697d6eba8d91294e87cb/tumblr_o76htcLTV21qgxv6vo3_1280.jpg" alt="" width="500"></p><p>It’s worth noting the cover that Donnell painted for <em>Sinister Barrier</em>.   As mentioned in the SFE article, Donnell was clearly reading the books that he illustrated, for here we see the evil Vril as floating orbs hovering over and impinging upon a tortured, helpless human figure.   This image is taken directly from the story, and is rather effective as a design, though not a very strong as an illustration.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://67.media.tumblr.com/e130834f62c7ba641ef7bd91a323590b/tumblr_o76htcLTV21qgxv6vo4_1280.jpg" alt="" width="500"></p><p>On a similar note, the cover for <em>Book of Ptath</em>, is a great design with uneven work in the illustration itself.   Almost characteristic to Donnell’s style, there are elements rendered in tight delineation, such as the ornamental sceptre, while surrounding it is a vague blurry ray, in this case spiraling upward as an ethereal beam of light.   The occult symbology here, like that of a tarot card, is perfect for the subject matter, the arcane <em>Book of Ptath</em>, which is hastily tossed in as a “book” shape in the corner.  Though the illustration is not particularly strong, the occult theme is effective, while the strong red and black shapes hit you like a punch in the nose.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://65.media.tumblr.com/0136c7400697593363be30d1d7064a2a/tumblr_o76htcLTV21qgxv6vo5_1280.jpg" alt="" width="500"></p><p>Finally, I would like to mention Donnell’s interpretation of <em>The Legion of Space</em>, which is nothing more than a sleek looking tower, rising in cold and windowless arrogance into a hot pink sky.  It has a clean, art deco streamlined look.   The font on the huge black band (which does not seem hand-written) that takes up nearly a third of the cover area, is crisp and perfect, as is the longhand script for the author’s name floating at the top.   The simplicity and power of this book jacket design should have Chip Kidd slapping his forehead in awe and admiration.  It is just sleek, pristine, arresting.   Few covers from small presses in the 1950s could touch those of A. J. Donnell, and it is worth giving them another look.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/DonnellAJ_SpacehoundsOfIPC_1948_md.jpg" alt="" width="463" height="683"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;In another post (about &lt;a href=&quot;http://yunchtime.net/?p=1826&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;blood moons and werewolves&lt;/a&gt;) I had occasi
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="illustration" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/illustration/"/>
    
      <category term="biography" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/biography/"/>
    
      <category term="design" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/design/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Island Under the Earth</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/island-under-the-earth/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/island-under-the-earth/</id>
    <published>2016-05-08T19:09:40.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Dillon_IslandUnderEarth_sm.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="1000"></p><blockquote><p>That inertia is the tendency of a body, when cold, to stay cold; and when hot, to stay hot &#8212; that during Star-flux when the thin white lines which cross and crisscross the skies of night tremble and waver and bend and then, for a long, mad moment, tremble and waver and melt and become compressed into tiny, brilliant points of light, and pulse and throb &#8212; that <strong>on such occasions wise mariners never put out of port, <em>for how can one steer?</em></strong> &#8212; that murrain-eels taint the water, which, once drunk of, turns the drinker into a homophage:  <strong>rogue, mad, a skulker, solitary, incapable of sustaining his brute life on any food but men’s flesh, and that but new-dead</strong> &#8212; that Earth-flux is when that fixed dark corner of the sky which conceals the gate of Human Hell changes form and moves &#8212;</p></blockquote><p>Avram Davidson, <em>The Island Under the Earth </em> (p.46)_</p><p>_</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Dillon_IslandUnderEarth_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;1000&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquo
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="quotes" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/quotes/"/>
    
      <category term="cannibalism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/cannibalism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>We need a monkey year...</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/we-need-a-monkey-year/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/we-need-a-monkey-year/</id>
    <published>2016-01-01T21:16:24.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.dbr.nu/vortex/new_year/newyear_2016_sm.jpg" alt="" width="420" height="610"></p><p>It has been a contradictory and confusing year, 2015.  At times it has been downright neurotic and malevolent, which I suppose is to be expected from a Year of the Goat!</p><p>We seem to have gotten farther into the woods, into the darkness, <a id="more"></a>and wound up all covered with cobwebs and mushroom spores falling off the rotting trunks of graying trees.   It’s time to bust out of this malaise and enliven ourselves!</p><p>The darker the woods, the brighter the Moon.</p><p>Now we are entering the Year of the Monkey!   That is a time of fun and mischief.   Forget about those malevolent leeches and the creaking gears of the corporate industrial machine, and let’s play a tune on them with our monkey-wrenches.   This nightmare only lasts as long as we are watching it.</p><p>No more re-runs.   Let’s all get creative and build a new world in 2016.  <a href="http://www.dbr.nu/vortex/new_year/" target="_blank" rel="external">Happy New Year, amigos!</a></p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.dbr.nu/vortex/new_year/newyear_2016_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;610&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a contradictory and confusing year, 2015.  At times it has been downright neurotic and malevolent, which I suppose is to be expected from a Year of the Goat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We seem to have gotten farther into the woods, into the darkness,
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="mushrooms" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/mushrooms/"/>
    
      <category term="New Year" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/New-Year/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Another Blood Moon, Another Howling</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/another-blood-moon-another-howling/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/another-blood-moon-another-howling/</id>
    <published>2015-10-24T20:50:57.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/bloodmoon_2015_sm.jpg" alt=""></p><p>What a <em>hullaballoo</em> was kicked up for the recent blood moon.  You’d think that a total eclipse occurring when the moon passes closest to Earth only happens, say … once every generation.   <em>Oh snap!</em>   <strong>Barely</strong> once in a generation.</p><p>I’ve been thinking back to the last time I saw such a moon:  it was on the deck of my small double-ender boat in Queensway Bay, Long Beach, California.  That little motor-sailer, with it’s oak frames and cedar planks was converted from a decommissioned Navy <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lifeboat_%28film%29" target="_blank">lifeboat</a>  into a 30 foot day sailer.  I bought it in decrepit condition as it was rotting and sinking in Naples Marina, and had it hauled out onto the dry-dock at Seal Beach Harbor;  but that’s a different story!   I remember standing on the deck, bobbing in the darkness as the water gently sloshed the hull, and how the mooring lines occasionally twanged when the boat rocked a certain way.   It was a mostly clear night. The lights of Los Angeles were far enough so that the huge blood red moon was fully visible overhead.  <strong>Thin strands of cloud seemed to slither behind and above the grayed out, slightly sinister lunar disk</strong>.  That vision of the ochre and crimson moon had me completely mesmerized.  I was scarcely aware of the chilling breeze over the water, the chiming halyards of the sailboat masts, and of the hours passing.   That eerie night, early in the Reagan years, is burned into my mind forever.  Thirty-three years ago!</p><p>This time around, Sophia and I camped out on our dining room floor, with pillows and beach blankets.  I swung open the plastic thermal-pane windows, which have a hinge that lets them tilt freely out of the their frame.   This gave us a clear line of sight, unobstructed by glass panes, trees, or clouds, so that we could look directly up at the mighty and mysterious glowing orb.   It was just as strange as the first time I’d seen a blood moon, and we couldn’t resist letting out a few wolf howls now and then.   <strong>Another blood moon, another howling.</strong></p><p>Another boost for the eternal popularity of werewolves.   Jeez, even Ubuntu has turned into a <a href="http://releases.ubuntu.com/15.10/" target="_blank">Wily Werewolf</a> all of a sudden.     “What’s a good werewolf yarn?” I thought, rummaging through my overflowing stacks of SF novels.   I loved <a href="http://yunchtime.net/?p=1261" target="_blank">Lycanthia</a> by Tanith Lee, and enjoyed Tim Powers <a href="http://amzn.to/204FqO5" target="_blank">Anubis Gates</a>,     but I wanted something I hadn’t read before.   Jack Williamson’s <a href="http://amzn.to/1GygbwM" target="_blank">Darker Than You Think</a>  was the obvious choice, and I was delighted to discover that this is really the best book I’ve ever read from that stalwart SF author.</p><p><img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/Wesso_WolvesOfDarkess.jpg" alt="" title="Illustration: Hans Wessolowski"></p><p>Williamson’s characters are always solid, his plots riveting, and his settings believable.    What I didn’t expect was the graceful prose and transcendental consciousness of the shape-shifters in <em>Darker Than You Think</em>.   <strong>Williamson takes his protagonist, a mediocre reporter named Will Barbee, from his self-pitying drunken existence, and runs him up and down the scales of doubt, suspicion, paranoia, fear and terror</strong> &#8212; and ultimately beyond his own psychic limitations, into a realm of predatory, savage ferocity, even madness!</p><p>In fact, I would say that the book <em>Darker Than You Think</em> transcends the run-of-the-mill science fiction thriller genre and verges on higher planes of literary merit, just like the book’s characters, who escape their physical bodies to become wild beasts of the night.   It is not so much in the solid and straight-forward narrative that the book shines, but in the weird places that Williamson takes us in the course of this traditional narrative.</p><p>When Barbee becomes a wolf, the readers are sent reeling drunkenly through the intensified smells of the night;  when he shape-shifts into a snake, our stomach muscles go twitching across the soil and the grass; when he slashes out to kill, we taste the horrible sweetness of human blood!   These scenes are so effortlessly knocked out, in his usual pulp style, we can almost relish what a great time Williamson must have had writing this book.   In this book, all of Williamson’s inhibitions are cast aside.   He gleefully gallops through the woods at midnight, with a gorgeous naked woman clinging to his back.  He is goaded onwards to find the darkest, cruelest parts of his mind, turned into a blood-thirsty ravening beast.   Another blood moon, another howling!</p><p><img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/CartierEdd_DarkerThanYouThink_1948_1.jpg" alt="" title="Illustration: Edd Cartier"></p><p>Weaving together the fantastic images of eroticism and violence, Williamson also provides plenty of plot twists.    At one point, the main character checks himself into an insane asylum, trying to stave off his transformation, which he nervously assumes cannot be real and must be a symptom of his troubled mind.   <em>Oh, the reader knows quite clearly that <strong>those dreams are perfectly real</strong>!  </em> But the wonderful tension that is drawn out between Barbee, the asylum’s psychologist, and the <em>femme fatale</em> is written with such delight, you can’t help but be aware of the author himself in these scenes, roaring with laughter and banging the keys of the typewriter with maniacal amusement.</p><p>Ultimately, <em>Darker Than You Think</em>, lives up to its title.   It does not deliver the typical <em>good-guy-punch-in-the-jaw ending</em>, but dashes off into unexpected zones of strangeness.  The inescapable conclusion is just as <a href="http://amzn.to/1WaWDWE" target="_blank">Curt Siodmak</a> said, in his Wolfman script:</p><p><strong>Even a man who is pure by heart</strong></p><p> <strong>And says his prayers by night</strong></p><p> <strong>May become a wolf</strong></p><p> <strong>When the wolfbane blooms</strong></p><p> <strong>and the Autumn Moon is bright.</strong></p><p><img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/DonnellAJ_DarkerThanYouThink_1948_sm.jpg" alt="" title="Illustration: A. J. Donnell"></p><p><img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/KleinDavidG_DarkerThanYouThink_1984.jpg" alt="" title="Painting: David G. Klein"></p><p><img src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/JonesJeff_DarkerThanYouThink_1968_sm.jpg" alt="" title="Painting:  Jeff Jones"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/bloodmoon_2015_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a &lt;em&gt;hullaballoo&lt;/em&gt; was kicked up for the recent bl
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="criticism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/criticism/"/>
    
      <category term="psychology" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/psychology/"/>
    
      <category term="moon" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/moon/"/>
    
      <category term="occult" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/occult/"/>
    
      <category term="werewolves" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/werewolves/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>MICE swarm in University Hall:  Mass Independent Comix Expo 2015</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/mice-swarm-in-university-hall/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/mice-swarm-in-university-hall/</id>
    <published>2015-10-18T22:20:57.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The <a href="http://www.micexpo.org/" target="_blank">MICE</a> invasion of Cambridge was a swarming crowd of anarchistic fun</strong>.   Hundreds of <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23MICE2015" target="_blank">comix-crazed attendees</a> jammed the halls of Leslie University, chatting with 200 comic artists and publishers.  Tables of eye candy stretched through the second floor of University Hall, connecting with additional jam-packed side rooms named after comix greats, such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Crumb" target="_blank">Crumb</a> Room, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julie_Doucet" target="_blank">Doucet</a> Hall, and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alison_Bechdel" target="_blank">Bechdel</a> Room.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_tables_sm.jpg" alt=""></p><p>You gotta love the idea of independent comix artists actually being recognized in the mundane society for their pure “genius” &#8212; proven by Alison Bechdel’s Westinghouse Genius Award in 2014!</p><p><strong>Here is a gang of fervent, possibly feverish, and yes, well, let’s face it, mostly starving artists</strong> who are so adamant, so tenacious, and so in-your-face diversified, that their official genius is the inventor of the gender-bias principle known as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechdel_test" target="_blank">Bechdel Test</a>.</p><p>Yo, MICE artists, kudos to the whole lot of you!   <strong>You are giant mice among scampering human conformists,</strong> in my book.</p><a id="more"></a><p>As I wandered around, I talked with <a href="http://www.hollyfoltz.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">Holly Foltz</a> and Jerel Dye, picking up Dye’s two issues of <a href="http://jereldye.com/blog/?tag=oneandroid" target="_blank">One Android</a>, with their robot vs. sea monster and robot stuck on a desert island themes.   As I happened to currently be reading the anthology <a href="http://amzn.to/1MMWx1u" target="_blank">Pseudo People</a>, I guess I couldn’t resist those android comics. They had a nice use of contrast and were painted with brush and ink.</p><p> <img src="http://jereldye.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/OAS_deepwaters_cover-229x300.jpg" alt="">    <a href="http://amzn.to/1MMWx1u" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/pseudo_people.jpg" alt=""></a></p><p>Another interesting discovery was the artist <a href="https://srcantirino.carbonmade.com/" target="_blank">Sally Cantirino</a>, who was busily painting a commission page in someone’s con sketchpad.   I liked the boldness of her attack on the clean page, and starting flipping through her mini-zines.   The one I liked best was <strong>Wise Blood</strong>, which was a series of female portraits with an occult mystical theme.  Her style is bold and has the sort of internal asymmetrical energy of Paul Pope.  The signature she sketched on the inside cover for me was the best of the show!</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Cantirino_WiseBlood_sm.jpg" alt=""></p><p>It was an unexpected treat to meet <a href="http://www.rsikoryak.com/" target="_blank">Robert Sikoryak</a>.   His twisted psychological mash-ups of classic novels and superheros comics were some of the greatest stuff I encountered in <a href="https://www.drawnandquarterly.com/" target="_blank">Drawn and Quarterly</a>.   In particular his <strong>reworking of <em>Crime and Punishment</em>, with <a href="http://www.sonicyouth.com/gossip/showthread.php?t=16422" target="_blank">Raskolinikov as Batman</a>, is an image that will stay burned in my mind forever</strong>.</p><p><a href="http://www.sonicyouth.com/gossip/showthread.php?t=16422" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/raskolnikov_batman.jpg" alt=""></a></p><p>Now he has collected the whole series of those mash-ups in a book, <a href="http://amzn.to/1LiC8z5" target="_blank">Masterpiece Comics</a>, well worth the price of admission.   At MICE, he signed for me a copy of his newest mini-zine &#8212; <strong>Sadistic Comics</strong> &#8212; published by <a href="http://rotlandpress.com/store-1/" target="_blank">Rotland Press</a>, as Rotland Dreadfuls #10.   This is a great little comic which recasts Wonder Woman from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sensation_Comics" target="_blank">Sensation Comics</a> as Justine from the novel by Marquis de Sade.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/sadistic_comics.jpg" alt=""></p><p>Each page is a single panel that portrays Wonder Woman / Justine in some sadistic situation as a series of psuedo covers.   As usual, Sikoryak’s peculiar social commentary and humor is over the top strange, disturbing, and hilarious.</p><p>The only panel I attended at MICE was the <a href="http://www.micexpo.org/2015/black-comics-and-cartoonists/" target="_blank">Black Independent Comics and Cartoonists</a> Panel, moderated by Tony Davis of <a href="http://www.themillionyearpicnic.com/" target="_blank">Million Year Picnic</a> fame, and including <a href="http://www.whittaylorcomics.com/comics.html" target="_blank">Whit Taylor</a>, <a href="http://www.buffalo.edu/home/feature_story/black-comix.html" target="_blank">John Jennings</a>, <a href="http://daygloayhole.tumblr.com/" target="_blank">Ben Passamore</a>, <a href="https://joelchristiangill.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">Joel Gill</a> and <a href="https://about.me/kuronekko" target="_blank">Micheline Hess</a>.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_panel.jpg" alt=""></p><p>Tony kicked off the session by recalling his growing up with comics, buying them in his Los Angeles neighborhood from a black-owned bookshop owned by Mr. Hall, and his forays up to Hollywood where a black high-school student worked at Burt Blum’s famous comic book section of the  <a href="http://www.comicsbeat.com/a-comics-shop-in-1965/" target="_blank">Cherokee Book Shop</a>.  In this sense, Tony felt as if his own experience of reading and buying comics was a normal part of his black community, even though the characters in the comics were almost all white people.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/BurtBlum_CherokeeBookShop_1965_sm.jpg" alt="Burt Blum in the original Cherokee Book Shop Comics Section"></p><p><center><br>  <strong>Burt Blum in the original Cherokee Book Shop Comics Section</strong><br></center>&nbsp;</p><p>The panelists then spent time introducing themselves and their experiences in growing up with comics and the point at which they were able to connect with black characters in comics.   Joel Gill thought it was the character <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spawn_%28comics%29" target="_blank">Spawn</a>, whose skin was ripped off and altered by a series of cosmic events, but who was actually an African-American, that was able to transcend the white and black stereotypes pervading the comic book pantheon.   The author of Spawn, Todd MacFarlane, has <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tqPrEQwBIkE" target="_blank">explained his motivation</a> in creating the character Spawn, in which <strong>he deliberately set out to remove the concept of race, as seen in the color of a person’s skin</strong>.</p><p>Ben Passamore had a similar reaction to Spawn, though John Jenning’s said the character he related to most was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daredevil_%28Marvel_Comics%29" target="_blank">Daredevil,</a> the white blind lawyer &#8212; not in terms of his race, but in terms of his attitude.  Daredevil was the guy who didn’t really have any superpower, except that he just didn’t know when to stop.  He was the “Man Without Fear,” who overcame his handiciap to swing around on cables and take on all opponents.  For Jennings, <strong>it was that fearless attitude of never giving up that he related to most</strong>.   Whit Taylor talked about growing up in a mostly white part of New Jersey, reading <em>Archie Comics</em>, and wondering why the characters Chuck Clayton and Nancy Woods were so totally devoid of personalities.   It was as if those characters had no black identity at all, and this made Whit wonder what a real African American comic book protagonist should be like.   The solution, of course, was to create her own comics and characters!</p><p>Micheline, who arrive some 45 minutes late to the panel, had an appropriate analogy about her experience of black characters in comics.   She said that in trying to identify with characters in comics, black people felt like “showing up to a banquet where everyone is already seated and eating.  You can stand there and have something to eat, but <strong>even though nobody will ask you to leave, what you really want is to make yourself a place at the table with everyone else!</strong>“    Tony Davis added: “Or it’s like showing up to a whole series of banquets where the food is always the same.”</p><p>Some of the recommended links and venues that the panelists mentioned to find out more about black independent comic creators were:</p><p><a href="http://afrofuturefest.com/" target="_blank">Afro Future Fest</a></p><p><a href="http://www.nypl.org/events/programs/2014/01/17/3rd-annual-black-comic-book-festival" target="_blank">Black Comic Book Festival</a> (held at the <a href="http://www.nypl.org/locations/schomburg" target="_blank">NYPL Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture</a>)</p><p><a href="http://bcaf.norcalmlkfoundation.org/" target="_blank">Black Comix Arts Festival</a></p><p><a href="http://blacksciencefictionsociety.com/" target="_blank">Black Science Fiction Society</a></p><p><a href="http://marinaomi.com/poc/cocindex.html" target="_blank">Cartoonist of Color Database</a></p><p><a href="http://Peepgamecomix.com" target="_blank">Peepgamecomix.com</a></p><p>After the panel session, I went to look for Ben Passamore.   His art really knocked me out, so I picked up both issues of <a href="http://daygloayhole.tumblr.com/" target="_blank">DAY GLO AY HOLE</a> and a mini-comic called <a href="https://www.radiatorcomics.com/shop/minicomics/goodbye/" target="_blank">Goodbye</a>. <strong>Ben’s work is something that I would call deeply human and angst-ridden, addressing the world we live in from a philosophical perspective</strong> that I found interesting and refreshing.</p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_dayglo_sm.jpg" alt=""></p><p>On the Black Independents panel, Ben remarked that growing up he felt very isolated and lonely.  He said: “I made violent and lonely comix when I was a kid, and I guess I still do.”  About how his readers approach him he also said  “Since my comics are so intensely personal, my blackness might be subjugated by the uncomfortable personal things that I write about.”   I could certainly relate to what he was saying, and I highly recommend taking some time to check out his stuff.</p><p>Once again, <strong>MICE, nibbled away at the status quo, leaving tooth marks on the shiny, brain-dead culture of corporate America.</strong>   Power to the Independents, and power to the people who support their fellow humans!</p><p><a href="http://<img%20src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_dayglo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;larger image&quot; />" target="_blank"><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_comix_sm.jpg" alt=""></a></p><p><img src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/MICE_program_2015_sm.jpg" alt=""></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.micexpo.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MICE&lt;/a&gt; invasion of Cambridge was a swarming crowd of anarchistic fun&lt;/strong&gt;.   Hundreds of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23MICE2015&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;comix-crazed attendees&lt;/a&gt; jammed the halls of Leslie University, chatting with 200 comic artists and publishers.  Tables of eye candy stretched through the second floor of University Hall, connecting with additional jam-packed side rooms named after comix greats, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Crumb&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Crumb&lt;/a&gt; Room, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julie_Doucet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Doucet&lt;/a&gt; Hall, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alison_Bechdel&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bechdel&lt;/a&gt; Room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/mice_tables_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You gotta love the idea of independent comix artists actually being recognized in the mundane society for their pure “genius” &amp;#8212; proven by Alison Bechdel’s Westinghouse Genius Award in 2014!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here is a gang of fervent, possibly feverish, and yes, well, let’s face it, mostly starving artists&lt;/strong&gt; who are so adamant, so tenacious, and so in-your-face diversified, that their official genius is the inventor of the gender-bias principle known as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bechdel_test&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bechdel Test&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yo, MICE artists, kudos to the whole lot of you!   &lt;strong&gt;You are giant mice among scampering human conformists,&lt;/strong&gt; in my book.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="comics" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/comics/"/>
    
      <category term="anarchism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/anarchism/"/>
    
      <category term="con report" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/con-report/"/>
    
      <category term="androids" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/androids/"/>
    
      <category term="equality" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/equality/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Russian Science Fiction Oddities from the John H. Costello Collection</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/russian-science-fiction-oddities-from-the-john-h-costello-collection/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/russian-science-fiction-oddities-from-the-john-h-costello-collection/</id>
    <published>2015-07-19T06:46:41.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The book and zine collection of John H. Costello, who passed away in early 2015, was donated to fandom recently at Readercon 26. Here I will take a quick look at some of the Russian language materials that I found among Costello’s collection.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CJkDtLAWIAAoOUj.jpg" alt="" width="540" height="720"></p><p>As I was digging through these large stacks of books, David Hartwell mentioned that Costello was a translator, so my attention was drawn to the foreign language books in the stacks, primarily in Russian and German.</p><p>After a little bit of follow-up research, I found out that Costello indeed had translated some of the works of Russian SF author, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kir_Bulychev" target="_blank">Kir Bulychev</a>. One of the items I found among the piles of old zines was Bulychev’s poetry collection <a href="https://fantlab.ru/edition30769" target="_blank">Chto nashe zhizn?</a> [What is our life?].</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/ShtoNasheZhizn_Bulychev.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="700"></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/Bulychev_inscription_sm.jpg" alt="" width="518" height="574"></p><p>This wasn’t particularly interesting, aside from the inscription to Costello inside the front cover, and the odd choices of clip art used to illustrate the poems.    I couldn’t quite figure out the poems:</p><p><em>In the world of little people,</em></p><p> <em>Many of the usual whores.</em></p><p> <em>But there are these whores</em></p><p> <em>Less  -  aunt,</em></p><p> <em>More  -  uncle.</em></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/Bulychev_title_page.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="719"></p><p>More interesting for me was the gorgeous copy of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tekhnika_Molodezhi" target="_blank"><em>Technika Molodezhni</em></a> (April 1975). I have always admired the gorgeous covers of this long-running magazine, but the copy I found in Costello’s collection is the first one I have actually held in my hands. It has all sorts of interesting contents and deserves a post of it’s own (coming soon!)</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/TechnikaMolodezhi_1975-04_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="676"></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/TechnikaMolodezhi_1975-04_back_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="671"></p><p>Definitely the most spectacular item I found was the Russian edition of Heinlein’s “<em>Door into Summer</em>“ [Dver v leta]. The wonderful cover art is uncredited. Nonetheless the glittering green eyes of the black cat over the sleeping astronaut are amazing and unforgettable!</p><p><img class="alignnone" src=" http://yunchtime.net/misc/Dver-b-leta_DoorIntoSummer_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="685"></p><p>Then there was the cartoonists collection that I found called <em>Joking Aside</em> [Shutki v storonu] from 1991. This is quite an interesting period for Soviet cartoonists, as they were testing the waters of Glasnost. I particularly liked the cartoons of Garif Bacyrov (1944-2004). According to <a href="http://www.tretyakovgallery.ru/en/collection/_show/author/_id/312" target="_blank">his biography</a> on the Tretyakov Gallery website, he was born in Kazakhstan at Akmolinsky Prison Camp for the wives of men who were accused of betraying their country. This perhaps explains the intensity of his images, like the wrecking ball cracking open the shoulder of an anthropomorphic brick building.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/Bacirof_WreckingBall_sm.jpg" alt="" width="553" height="679"></p><p>Another cartoonist I liked in this book was Mikhael Zlatkovskii, who also had a cynical sense of humor, of the type you might find in Zap Comix. This iconic illustration &#8212; apparently about the dangers of prostitution &#8212; also appeared in <a href="http://www.cartoonblues.com/forum/viewtopic.php?f=37&#038;t=10731" target="_blank">other publications</a> around the same time.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/zlatkovskii_prostitution_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="515"></p><p>Then there was the humorous illustration of two opposing camps of protestors. The farm animals marching under the sign: “BREAD!” facing off against humans who are marching under the sign “MEAT!” Somehow, this illustration by I. Novikov seems relevant today, too, in the context of animal rights &amp; veganism against carnivores. But I don’t really know what it meant in Russia in 1990…</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/Novikov_BreadMeat_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="286"></p><p>For the curious you can download the whole book of <em>Joking Aside</em> as a <a href="https://yadi.sk/d/eSVmZJIf8H1Hq" target="_blank">PDF</a>.</p><p>From the fannish perspective, probably the most historically interesting find was a copy of <a href="http://fantlab.ru/work229652" target="_blank">FENZOR #1</a>, a Russian fanzine edited by Sergei Berezhnoi and published in May 1990. This is just the coolest little fanzine (about 11 x 14cm in size), very nicely printed in crisp type and with neat line drawings. The inscription shows that the editor was keen to share the premiere issue of FENZOR with his first American friend, John (Costello)!</p><p><img class="alignnone" src=" http://yunchtime.net/misc/fenzor_n1_1990_cover_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="687"></p><p><img class="alignnone" src=" http://yunchtime.net/misc/fenzor_n1_1990_toc_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="693"></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/fenzor_n1_1990_back_sm.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="701"></p><p>By far the strangest item I found in Costello’s collection was a custom-made fannish pinback button featuring a Japanese manga-style vampire. The vampire appears above the balloon-style font that says: KISS [Nimta]. On the upper left, in the vampire’s hair, are the letters NTTM, which I am guessing as referring to the <em>&lt;a href=”<a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D1%82%D1%80" target="_blank" rel="external">https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A6%D0%B5%D0%BD%D1%82%D1%80</a></em>%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%83%D1%87%D0%BD%D0%BE-%D1%82%D0%B5%D1%85%D0%BD%D0%B8%D1%87%D0%B5%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%BE<em>%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%80%D1%87%D0%B5%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%B0</em>%D0%BC%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B4%D1%91%D0%B6%D0%B8” target=”<em>blank”&gt;Tsentr nauchno-tekhnicheskogo tvorchestva molodozhi</em>, or the</p><p>Center for Scientific and Technical Creativity of Youth.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src=" http://yunchtime.net/misc/NTTM_Kiss_button_ca_1990_raw.jpg" alt="" width="520" height="507"></p><p>This NTTM seems worty of further research. It appears to have been the legacy institution built to replace the old Komsomol (Young Pioneers) of the Soviet Union, as a way to promote the sciences for young people in the new Russia. Apparently it was built on the crumbling and despirited edifice of the Communist cadre system. One can only assume that the usage here on this badge is tongue-in-cheek, and a sort of snarky reference to the “authority” of their fannish mission.</p><p>The text encircling the badge is more what I would expect: “<strong>Unusual research into the Mystical, Fantastic, and Absurd</strong> [Neobychnyye Issledovaniya Mistika Fantastika Absurd].” </p><p>The transition of Science Fiction fandom from the Soviet period to the Russian Federation, has got to be interesting, though I know so little about it. These lucky finds among the items of John H. Costello’s library are the first window I have had on this bit of fannish history. Hopefully these leads will take me down some interesting pathways.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/NTTM_Kiss_button_ca_1990_English.png" alt="" width="520" height="507"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;The book and zine collection of John H. Costello, who passed away in early 2015, was donated to fandom recently at Readercon 26. Here I w
      
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="fandom" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/fandom/"/>
    
      <category term="zines" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/zines/"/>
    
      <category term="cartoonists" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/cartoonists/"/>
    
      <category term="Russia" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/Russia/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Readercon 2015:  Veering Towards Pluto</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/readercon-2015-veering-towards-pluto/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/ARTS/readercon-2015-veering-towards-pluto/</id>
    <published>2015-07-14T01:27:30.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://readercon.org/" target="_blank">Readercon</a> is generally my favorite con of the year, and in 2015 Readercon was up to the usual standard of fun times and excellence.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/readercon26.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="407"></p><p>The guests of honor <a href="http://nicolagriffith.com/" target="_blank">Nicola Griffith</a> and <a href="http://blogs.roosevelt.edu/gwolfe/" target="_blank">Gary K Wolfe</a> were on hand throughout, and the memorial GOH was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joanna_Russ" target="_blank">Joanna Russ</a>.  How could you go wrong?   Indeed there were no less than three sessions on the life and work of Joanna Russ, including the participation of the author’s long-time associates:  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Freund" target="_blank">Jim Freund,</a> <a href="http://www.davidghartwell.com/" target="_blank">David Hartwell,</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Dirda" target="_blank">Michael Dirda</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Drummond" target="_blank">Ron Drummond</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_R._Delany" target="_blank">Samuel R. Delany</a>.</p><p>Freund told some great stories about the early days of his career at WBAI Radio in New York, when he was literally living in the station offices, and broadcasting his radio show, “<a href="http://wbai.org/program.php?program=70" target="_blank">Hour of the Wolf</a>,”   five days a week at 5:00am.   One time Freund called up Russ at about 8pm and invited her to join him for an interview on <em>Hour of the Wolf</em>.  Russ declined the interview, but she did invite him out to eat at a nearby diner.   The meal turned into an eight hour long conversation.  </p><p>Finally, having talked through the night, at about 4:30am, Russ asked to stop over at the Radio Station to use the bathroom on her way home, while Freund was getting ready for his show.   Just as he was going live, Russ stopped by the control room to wave good-bye, and she heard Freund say into the microphone:  <strong>“This is the Hour of the Wolf, and my guest today is Joanna Russ.”   The first words Russ spoke on that particular live broadcast were:  “You motherfucker!   I’m going to kill you!”  </strong></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/joanna-russ_sm.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="399"></p><p>Which she subsequently did, by killing off the character based on Freund in her novel, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0819567590/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0819567590&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=LTXJHAKQG2FLNFLJ" target="_blank">We Who Are About To</a>.</p><a id="more"></a><p>Michael Dirda reminisced about his days at Cornell, where he and Joanna Russ became friends, and how she gave him a crash course in Science Fiction criticism when he first began to review SF for the Washington Post.   David Hartwell told stories about what a dynamic and fun person Russ was to be around, for example, the night when she corralled some of her fellow writers and got them all to contribute lines to a story that she decided to compose on the spot:  _<a href="http://vms.pdv-systeme.de/users/martinv/pgg/08U/08U010.html" target="_blank">Useful Phrases for the Tourist</a>_ (1972)</p><p>In this pastiche of a tourist booklet, we find some memorable lines such as:  <strong>“Madam, this bed/nest is alive,”  “My head is not interchangeable,” and “At what hour does the lovelorn princess fling herself into the flaming volcano?  May we participate?.”   </strong></p><p>Hartwell pointed this out as a way of balancing the customary view of Russ as determined, combative, and intense.   She was all those things too, as Ron Drummond added with a short reading of a wonderful anecdote from his student days at University of Washington.</p><p>In one of Russ’s lectures, she explained to her students how Herman Melville’s career trajectory took a downward spiral after the dismal sales of Moby Dick; ironically, the most famous of his works more than a century after his death.  While his advance payments had been continuously rising up until <em>Moby Dick</em>, in his subsequent novel, <em>Pierre</em>, they shrank, and when he submitted the following novel, <em>Isle of the Cross</em>, his publisher actually rejected the manuscript.   Furious at this turn of events Melville burned not only the submitted manuscript for <em>Isle of the Cross</em>, but all of his draft copies and notes as well, thus destroying the book for all time.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/white-island_isles-of-shoals.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="399"></p><p>At this point of the lecture, Joanna Russ said that if she had a time machine, she would travel back to to visit that author.  Not in order to save the manuscript of <em>Isle of the Cross</em> from the flames, but to strangle Melville for having destroyed it.   <strong>This image of Joanna Russ, acting out the strangling of Herman Melville in front of the classroom by wringing his imaginary neck, was the perfect characterization of her intense relationship with literature and and a demonstration of her passion to correct the errors of literary history.</strong></p><p>Another great panel this year was a tribute to the publication of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0375706682/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0375706682&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=NKOTVCVUA2WP2A6W" target="_blank"><em>Dhalgren</em></a> by Samuel R. Delany, first published forty years ago in the famous Bantam Paperback edition.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/dhalgren.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="333"></p><p><em>Dhalgren</em> is an intense book, to which each person has their own unique and strong reactions.   Shira Lipkin said that she first encountered <em>Dhalgren</em> after ending up in Las Vegas, Nevada, and living with a rough crowd of drug-using punks.  “I was having my personal apocalypse at the time, so it seemed to make perfect sense to enter the city of Bellona.”</p><p>John Stevens discovered <em>Dhalgren</em> when he asked a teacher, who had been giving him science fiction recommendations, to suggest something “more challenging.”   What the teacher gave him was <em>Dhalgren</em>.   “That set the bar very high,” Stevens said, “and when I finished <em>Dhalgren</em>, I asked for something else to read on the same level of literary excellence and challenge.   At which point he handed me a copy of <em>Ulysses</em>.   <strong>So as it turned out, <em>Dhalgren</em> not only turned me on to the possibilities of science fiction, but to highest standards of literature itself.</strong>“</p><p>There were several other really great panels that I attended, including one on Mystery and Speculative Fiction Crossovers.   In the Mystery panel, <a href="http://www.greergilman.com/about.html" target="_blank">Greer Gilman</a> was in fine form, reeling off observations such as:</p><p><strong>“Fantasy reifies metaphors.   There really <em>is</em> a black tarantula on that slice of angel food cake!”</strong>   Or:  “In the SFnal mystery story there is an underlying tension between the soluble and the insoluble.   <strong>You can actually solve the mystery, but you cannot solve the World that you are in.</strong>“</p><p>Then in the Anthropocene panel, contemplating the fate of our own planet Earth, Michael Daley asked:  “Are we merely mammals?  Or as Human Beings will we make use of our consciousness to stop these destructive behaviors in time to save our species?”</p><p>Vandana Singh, a particle-physicist by training, had some great points to make in this session.  “Are we in the Anthropocene, or in the Capitalocene?  What we are missing in Capitalism (and all the other -isms) is the relationship of humanity to Nature.  <strong>Can we remove the delusion of being separated from Nature in time to save ourselves?</strong>   We must decide, do we want a world that is hot as Hell and completely unlivable?  Or do we want a world that is very inhospitable, but where we can at least scrape by as a species?   I think this is an opportunity for SF writers to show their revolutionary potential.   By presenting scenarios of survival as communities, we can inform people of the chances that humans may still have.”</p><p>Deluca was less optimistic:  “What is SF’s revolutionary potential?  I’m skeptical about us writers being able to change these enormous systems that are firmly entrenched.”</p><p>Michael J. Daley wondered:  “What is the best motivator (as a theme in SF)?  The terror of total destruction, or hope for technological solutions?   Maybe in the latter category we could think about Solarpunk…”</p><p>Vandana Singh concluded:  “Technological solutions to global climate change won’t work unless they include social solutions.  The bottom line for or survival right now is that we must get off our addiction to fossil fuels.”</p><p>Wandering around the con, I ended up chatting with <a href="http://www.frankwu.com/" target="_blank">Frank Wu</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ted_Chiang" target="_blank">Ted Chiang</a>.  Wu asked Chiang how he came up with the idea for the story <em>Exhalation</em> (<a href="http://www.lightspeedmagazine.com/fiction/exhalation/" target="_blank">published in Lightspeed</a>).    Ted said there were two main inspirations for the story, the first being P. K. Dick’s story  <em>The Electric Ant</em>, which begins with the protagonist injuring his arm and going to see the doctor to have it patched up.   The doctor scans him and says: <strong>“Well, I can’t treat you because you are a robot, so you will have to go see a robot repair specialist.”</strong>   Shocked to discover that he is not a human being, the protagonist gets his arm fixed at the robot repair place then goes home to look up his own specifications on the central computer.   Given a certain sequence of pressure points, he then proceeds to open himself up.  His midriff splits open and he is astonished to see, in fact, that he is a robot, full of wires and clockwork mechanisms, at the center of which is a small punch-tape slowly unreeling through a spool.</p><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0785139818/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&#038;camp=1789&#038;creative=390957&#038;creativeASIN=0785139818&#038;linkCode=as2&#038;tag=diambayrese-20&#038;linkId=4DY5NT2FXSG7S5IS" target="_blank" title="Comic book adaption by David Mack and Pascal Alixe"><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/elect_ant.jpg" alt="" width="608" height="229"></a></p><p>The second inspiration for <em>Exhalation</em> was in a section of a novel where there is a long digression about the physical nature of the Universe, and in which it is explained that people don’t eat food to obtain energy.   It is pointed out that food is a very low entropy energy source, and that having eaten food, people actually radiate heat and energy at a much higher rate of entropy.   This low energy to high energy phase change is what inspired Chiang for the argon in <em>Exhalation</em>.</p><p>This was a great introduction to <a href="http://www.lightspeedmagazine.com/fiction/exhalation/" target="_blank">Chiang’s story</a>, which I read the same night and very much enjoyed.   Especially the way in which Chiang adapted the P. K. Dick idea of the robot opening his mechanism up to look inside.  In <em>Exhalation</em>, <strong>the main character sets up an elaborate surgical apparatus so that: “I would then be able to dissect my own brain… the most beautifully complex engine I had ever beheld.”</strong>   Very interesting!</p><p>One unexpected event at this year’s Readercon, was a whole room full of free books.   Long time fan, John H. Costello, passed away in 2015, and his book collection was set up for anyone to sort through and take home.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CJkDtLAWIAAoOUj.jpg" alt="" width="540" height="720"></p><p>Costello, in addition to be an archeologist, was a translator, who published some English editions of the Russian SF author, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kir_Bulychev" target="_blank">Kir Bulychev</a>.    Among the cool finds that I dug out of the various piles and boxes of Costello’s collection, was a rare copy of   _<a href="https://fantlab.ru/edition30769" target="_blank">Chto nashe zhizn?</a>_  [What is our life?] …  the signed copy #32 out of an edition of 500 copies.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://yunchtime.net/misc/ShtoNasheZhizn_Bulychev.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="700"></p><p>This strange little book, along with some other eye-catching treats from back in the USSR that I found in the Costello collection, are worth pursuing in a follow up post, so keep tuned to channel Yunchtime!    And thanks to John Costello, who seems to have been a fellow that I would have enjoyed talking to, and whom I regret not having met on this particular journey.</p><p>Mixing with the great people in attendance, of course, is what makes the con.  And I really enjoyed catching up with Dianne Weinstein, Mark Borok, Chip Delany, George Morgan, Arielle Saiber, Neil Clarke, Scott Edelman, Darrell Schweitzer, and Ed Koenig.   I also met two editors, Tom Easton and Will Whalley.  It’s hard to wind down afterwards, and realize that a whole trip around the sun will transpire before Readercon 27.   Considering the recent Sad and Rabid Puppies slates kerfluffle, which swept up many fanac hours over recent months, Readercon was completely upbeat. I barely heard any mention of the Hugo slate controversy, with the exception of a few comments in the Who Owns SF panel.   It was really a <em>relaxcon</em> this year, possibly helped along by a bunch of fans kicking up their heels at the 80s dance.</p><p><img class="alignnone" title="(c) Fran Wilde" src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/CJmpi33WoAEeW3g.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="800"></p><p>For me, it was a fine new pile of treasures to read, and a fine time with my fellow travelers of the SFnal Universe.   <strong>Aloha, everyone, and Mahalo!</strong></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://readercon.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Readercon&lt;/a&gt; is generally my favorite con of the year, and in 2015 Readercon was up to the usual standard of fun times and excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://yunchtime.net/misc/readercon26.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;407&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guests of honor &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicolagriffith.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicola Griffith&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.roosevelt.edu/gwolfe/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gary K Wolfe&lt;/a&gt; were on hand throughout, and the memorial GOH was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joanna_Russ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joanna Russ&lt;/a&gt;.  How could you go wrong?   Indeed there were no less than three sessions on the life and work of Joanna Russ, including the participation of the author’s long-time associates:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Freund&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jim Freund,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidghartwell.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;David Hartwell,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Dirda&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michael Dirda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ron_Drummond&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ron Drummond&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samuel_R._Delany&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samuel R. Delany&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freund told some great stories about the early days of his career at WBAI Radio in New York, when he was literally living in the station offices, and broadcasting his radio show, “&lt;a href=&quot;http://wbai.org/program.php?program=70&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hour of the Wolf&lt;/a&gt;,”   five days a week at 5:00am.   One time Freund called up Russ at about 8pm and invited her to join him for an interview on &lt;em&gt;Hour of the Wolf&lt;/em&gt;.  Russ declined the interview, but she did invite him out to eat at a nearby diner.   The meal turned into an eight hour long conversation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, having talked through the night, at about 4:30am, Russ asked to stop over at the Radio Station to use the bathroom on her way home, while Freund was getting ready for his show.   Just as he was going live, Russ stopped by the control room to wave good-bye, and she heard Freund say into the microphone:  &lt;strong&gt;“This is the Hour of the Wolf, and my guest today is Joanna Russ.”   The first words Russ spoke on that particular live broadcast were:  “You motherfucker!   I’m going to kill you!”  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://yunchtime.net/misc/joanna-russ_sm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;399&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which she subsequently did, by killing off the character based on Freund in her novel, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0819567590/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0819567590&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=LTXJHAKQG2FLNFLJ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;We Who Are About To&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="ARTS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/ARTS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="con report" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/con-report/"/>
    
      <category term="readercon" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/readercon/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Surrealist Path of Harry O. Morris</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/the-surrealist-path-of-harry-o-morris/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/HUMAN-BEINGS/the-surrealist-path-of-harry-o-morris/</id>
    <published>2015-06-29T02:35:29.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/MorrisHarryO_Maldoror2_sm.png" alt="" width="500" height="489"></p><p>It was great to finally read _<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1613470010/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1613470010&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=6YQ7Q3NIFKSO3UXQ" target="_blank">Harry O. Morris  -  Artist Portfolio</a>_ from Centipede Press.   Flipping through the lush images that take up most of the 320 pages, you can journey through the strangeness that has characterized the long career of this remarkable artist.</p><p>I am really lucky to have known Harry from way back when.  We first met in Albuquerque in the mid-1970s.   At that time, Harry’s friend and fellow artist, Leslie Hall, was working in the same office as my father.   Leslie was a frequent visitor to our house and noticed that I was a rabid reader of science fiction.  He recommended J.G. Ballard and loaned me a copy of the anthology,_ <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0140024999/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0140024999&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=RBSM7LTLNKUNQGBK" target="_blank">Terminal Beach</a>_.</p><p>This was a cool discovery for me, around the age of 13, when I suddenly became aware of the difference between New Wave science fiction writers and the various space opera and <em>Campbellian</em> authors that I had been reading.   Pieces of the jigsaw puzzle fell into place, and I had a whole new appreciation of books by Spinrad, Moorcock, M. John Harrison, and Samuel R. Delany.   Not only did I re-read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0006C2HZI/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B0006C2HZI&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=XXRHMVEVDPDAZI35" target="_blank"><em>Driftglass</em></a>, with a whole new kind of poetic awareness, but I shortly devoured all of Ballard’s books, and soon found that Van Vogt no longer satisfied in the way that R. A. Lafferty, Roger Zelazny, and Stanislaw Lem did.</p><p>So in this friendly context, I took more interest in the peculiar artwork of Leslie Hall, and his friend and collaborator, Harry O. Morris, who had both been working with the techniques of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0807610232/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0807610232&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=DTIEBE3YJEZCUE7S" target="_blank">Max Ernst</a> and <a href="http://cargocollective.com/veronika-veil/SATTY" target="_blank">Wilfried Sätty</a>, pushing the surrealistic and horror aspects of those methods as far as they could go.   At that time, I enjoyed being peripherally involved in Leslie’s art projects:  cutting out old engraved plates from books with X-acto knives and moving the pieces of unrelated images around to create surrealist collages.   Some of the images that Leslie came up with were published in limited edition portfolios by Harry O. Morris, including a set from 1982 called, <em>Inclement Weather.</em></p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HallLeslie_ParlourGames_1982_(C)sm.png" alt="" width="600" height="777"></p><p>Hanging around with Leslie Hall, soon resulted in meeting Harry O. Morris, who had been working on similar art projects.  That is when I first found out about his Lovecraftian zine, <a href="http://zinewiki.com/Nyctalops" target="_blank">Nyctalops</a>, which is now considered a classic.</p><p>I admired Harry from the start.   Here was a fellow who clearly didn’t really “fit in” with the rest of society, and yet he had his own print shop and typesetting operation, and was creating some really astonishing and interesting art.   Here was someone who I could talk to about the Franju film, _<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/6301305140/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=6301305140&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=EUQBAXTIHBLKMTBE" target="_blank">Yeux sans Visage</a>_ [Eyes Without a Face], and who not only knew the film, but knew the horror of it, on a deeply personal level.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Morris_eyeswithoutaface.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="739"></p><a id="more"></a><p>Harry seemed to be practically a hermit.  He lived in an old house near a bread factory just SE of downtown Albuquerque.   The place was nestled in a semi-industrial strip next to I-25, and was always slightly aromatic of freshly-baked bread wafting from the industrial vents of the nearby Butterkrust bread factory.  In those days, the thing that struck me most about Harry Morris was that he had somehow become deeply affected with a sense of total dread for the Universe and all it’s inhabitants.</p><p>He wasn’t just goofing around, trying to get sympathy, or trying to put on an act of being cool, aloof, or mysterious.   Harry actually had some kind of terrifying inner knowledge about the dark side of the Universe that naturally drew him to the works of H. P. Lovecraft.  He was able to explore his own consciousness with an extreme sensitivity to terror, to dread, to the sense of fear and trembling that grabs us when we know &#8212; <em>deep in our bones</em> &#8212; that something is very wrong about this plane of existence.</p><p>The way we perceive reality, if you ask me, is not only a misinterpretation, but more of a collective delusion, salted by our own personal blind spots.   <strong>Hiding around the edges of this, the elder Gods are creeping in, they are squishing their narcotic tentacles into the tubes of our brain… while the music of the spheres is grinding away like machinery with misaligned gears</strong>.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HOM_illo1.jpg" alt="" width="450" height="649"></p><p>In my opinion, this is why Harry (and many of the rest of us) so appreciated artworks that explored the apprehension of these darker places in our consciousness.  Take for example, the movie <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00A5IXYR8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00A5IXYR8&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=KBKFPXALLUAVFKFV" target="_blank"><em>Eraserhead</em></a> by David Lynch.   <strong>The off-key, and awkward moments of our lives &#8212; <em>when our essential misfit with the rest of space and time becomes a little too obvious</em> &#8212; that is the space where Harry O. lives.</strong>   That is where his art comes from, and his eery ability to get under our skin.</p><p>He’s a genius really.   He is the only practicing and totally uncompromising surrealist I have ever met.   And for that I will always thank him!</p><p>It was a treat to sit around, in those days, with Harry and Leslie, working on collages, or making up “exquisite corpse” poems, in which we would take turns creating the weirdest Gothic horror doggerel you can imagine.  Both Harry and Leslie were the only two people I knew who both spoke and lived the language of surrealism.  They were always introducing me to new writers and artists, like Yves Tanguy (suddenly Richard Powers had a context!), or Le Comte de Lautreamont and his nightmare classic, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0811200825/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0811200825&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=YPE4XNKQTQPE5RBY" target="_blank"><em>Les Chants de Maldoror</em></a>.   I picked up a Grove paperback edition of this over at the Living Batch bookstore, and was at once mesmerized by its dark and misanthropic aspects.</p><p>What really amazed me was the quality of the art and writing that these “unknowns” were creating for <em>Nyctalops</em>, which Harry was publishing himself (as the Silver Scarab Press).</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.philsp.com/data/images/n/nyctalops_197705_n13.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="517"></p><p>There were drawings and photo-montages lying around on Harry’s production table by people like Bill McCabe, J.K. Potter, alongside of typeset stories by G. Sutton Brieding and editorials by Harry Morris that blew me away.   <strong><em>These guys could write in their own voice! </em></strong>  I started to appreciate and understand the connections between Poe, Verlaine, Huysmans, Rimbaud, Vian, Gracq, and H. P. Lovecraft.   I suppose the main thing I got out this was the fact that writing didn’t just “happen” like spontaneous combustion, but was a continuous process involving the author and his readers.  Sometimes the readers who provided feedback were only a few immediate friends.  Sometimes they were correspondents you’d never met.</p><p>And so you end up with Harry discovering the works of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=as_li_ss_tl?_encoding=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&keywords=thomas%20ligotti&linkCode=ur2&qid=1435605691&rh=i%3Aaps%2Ck%3Athomas%20ligotti&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=PNEEG2U2LSPZ7WQB" target="_blank">Thomas Ligotti</a>, and being so convinced of their quality, he decided to print them himself on the underground equipment of Silver Scarab Press.   The rest of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Songs_of_a_Dead_Dreamer" target="_blank"><em>that</em> story</a> is history!</p><p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00166I4KA/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=B00166I4KA&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=IMDGCFSIM4PHOUX2" target="_blank"><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/MorrisHarryO_SongsDeadDreamer_sm.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="751"></a></p><p>Since putting aside the old Gestetner mimeo machine, Harry had assembled the pieces of a high quality photo-offset printing plant.   In 1979 or 1980, while I was living in New York City, I asked Harry to print up 100 copies of a cover that I was planning to use for a Science Fiction zine, called <em>Black Hole SF</em>.  It was an interesting collage done by Leslie Hall, who had kindly given me permission to use it.   Too bad that I was too busy dropping out of college and never got around to publishing the zine, though I still have the perfectly printed covers that Harry sent me.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HallLeslie_BlackHoleSF_1979_sm.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="673"></p><p>Soon after dropping out of college, I washed up in Albuquerque again, and in the Spring of 1981 Harry sold me his old mimeograph, which had been collecting dust in the corner of his basement.   I promptly named the machine Blond Beest, and starting printing copies of an anarchist zine called <em>Magickal Dispatch</em>.   Unfortunately, it was not really up to any standard, and was soon abandoned.  But I have to hand it again to Harry O., who was quite willing to sell me his old Gestetner, even on the flimsy premise that an unemployed college drop-out was going to be able to publish an anarchist zine.</p><p>Harry was always innovating.  He had amassed a bunch of great old-school printing equipment in his basement, including a large format copy camera, typesetter, light-tables, and some primordial digital equipment that he was using to invent his own processes.   He loved to posterize images to the point at which they became blurry abstractions, and he loved to screen images to give them grainy textures.   Most of this he did with traditional photographic and pre-press screening techniques.   But Harry was also an early adopter of digital technology.   Although he claims to not know much about computers, he was tinkering with them even in the early 1980s, using an Amiga, probably ten years before I owned my first cheap Windows box (running DOS 3.1).</p><p>One of the digital gizmos Harry set up was an old surplus CCTV video monitor, of the kind used at banks for security cameras.  There was a long delay of the the response time as the cheap sensor recorded vertical lines and processed them through DigiView software (running on his Amiga) to a thermal paper printer. Once when I was visiting Harry in the early 1980s he set up the monitor and took an exposure, in which I was to hold very still for about ten seconds, then slowly turn my head to the side.    This delay caused the resulting image to be very weird indeed.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HOM_Lex_thermal_video_image_med.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="482"></p><p>Harry has a knack for figuring out how surreal and distorted images can be used to powerful effect, without simply making them into unintelligible nonsense.   He is always carefully testing and noodling around to get the exact image that he is after, which is a personal thing for him.  It reminds me of Castenada’s lucid dreaming practice, in which you are trying to see and control your own hands in a dream.   Harry is continuously pursuing this phantom image in his mind, taking inspiration from Max Ernst, Satty, Franju, and other surrealists.</p><p>As Breton himself set out in the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0472061828/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0472061828&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=CGRLHQ6DMTER7PEJ" target="_blank"><em>Manifesto</em></a>:  <strong>I believe in the future resolution of these two states, <em>dream and reality</em>, which are seemingly so contradictory, into a kind of absolute reality, a surreality, if one may so speak.   ..  We really live by our fantasies when we give free reign to them.</strong></p><p>What I still admire about Harry O. Morris is the free reign that he gives to his own imagination.   Of course, he is not immune to the slings and arrows of daily life, and has to put up with the general dread and malaise of living in the same world of greedy, violent idiots as the rest of us.   But he never once gave in to the <em>status quo</em>.   Harry lives life the way he chooses to live it.   And he does so with a flair and a panache that reflects his own tastes and (sometimes morbid) humor.</p><p>At the entry of his house there used to be an old sliced open basketball, mounted on a globe stand, and with its skin peeled away in long irregular strips.  <strong>Even as you walk through the door of his house you are punched in the nose with a metaphor:  <em>a world in decay, rotten and dissected for you to plainly see!</em></strong></p><p>And as you turn to face strangeness upon strangeness, you enter Harry’s place:  where the candelabras reach out from the walls to light your way, and beasts sit gently snorting streams of smoke on the other side of the mirror.   This is Harry’s place!   With a tower shaped like a witch’s hat on top, and circled round by a fence made of blackened cast iron spikes.</p><p><strong>Thanks for this reality that you fashioned in the midst of utter mediocrity, Harry, for this surreality that is it’s own transcendental path to other worlds!</strong></p><p>When I was still a whipper-snapper and hadn’t seen much, you demonstrated beyond any doubt the lasting strength of being oneself, come Hell or high water.   It has benefited me ever since.</p><p>Now, as the new Centipede Press _<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1613470010/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=1613470010&linkCode=as2&tag=diambayrese-20&linkId=6YQ7Q3NIFKSO3UXQ" target="_blank">Artists Portfolio</a>_ will attest, the bizarre and arresting visuals of Harry O. Morris are in a class to themselves!   Hope you all can find a copy and enjoy it as much as I did.</p><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HOM_illo2.jpg" alt="" width="446" height="600"></p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/MorrisHarryO_Maldoror2_sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;489&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to finally read _&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1613470010/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1613470010&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=6YQ7Q3NIFKSO3UXQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harry O. Morris  -  Artist Portfolio&lt;/a&gt;_ from Centipede Press.   Flipping through the lush images that take up most of the 320 pages, you can journey through the strangeness that has characterized the long career of this remarkable artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am really lucky to have known Harry from way back when.  We first met in Albuquerque in the mid-1970s.   At that time, Harry’s friend and fellow artist, Leslie Hall, was working in the same office as my father.   Leslie was a frequent visitor to our house and noticed that I was a rabid reader of science fiction.  He recommended J.G. Ballard and loaned me a copy of the anthology,_ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0140024999/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0140024999&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=RBSM7LTLNKUNQGBK&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Terminal Beach&lt;/a&gt;_.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a cool discovery for me, around the age of 13, when I suddenly became aware of the difference between New Wave science fiction writers and the various space opera and &lt;em&gt;Campbellian&lt;/em&gt; authors that I had been reading.   Pieces of the jigsaw puzzle fell into place, and I had a whole new appreciation of books by Spinrad, Moorcock, M. John Harrison, and Samuel R. Delany.   Not only did I re-read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0006C2HZI/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B0006C2HZI&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=XXRHMVEVDPDAZI35&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Driftglass&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, with a whole new kind of poetic awareness, but I shortly devoured all of Ballard’s books, and soon found that Van Vogt no longer satisfied in the way that R. A. Lafferty, Roger Zelazny, and Stanislaw Lem did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this friendly context, I took more interest in the peculiar artwork of Leslie Hall, and his friend and collaborator, Harry O. Morris, who had both been working with the techniques of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0807610232/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0807610232&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=DTIEBE3YJEZCUE7S&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Max Ernst&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://cargocollective.com/veronika-veil/SATTY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wilfried Sätty&lt;/a&gt;, pushing the surrealistic and horror aspects of those methods as far as they could go.   At that time, I enjoyed being peripherally involved in Leslie’s art projects:  cutting out old engraved plates from books with X-acto knives and moving the pieces of unrelated images around to create surrealist collages.   Some of the images that Leslie came up with were published in limited edition portfolios by Harry O. Morris, including a set from 1982 called, &lt;em&gt;Inclement Weather.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/HallLeslie_ParlourGames_1982_(C)sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;777&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanging around with Leslie Hall, soon resulted in meeting Harry O. Morris, who had been working on similar art projects.  That is when I first found out about his Lovecraftian zine, &lt;a href=&quot;http://zinewiki.com/Nyctalops&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nyctalops&lt;/a&gt;, which is now considered a classic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admired Harry from the start.   Here was a fellow who clearly didn’t really “fit in” with the rest of society, and yet he had his own print shop and typesetting operation, and was creating some really astonishing and interesting art.   Here was someone who I could talk to about the Franju film, _&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/6301305140/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=6301305140&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=diambayrese-20&amp;linkId=EUQBAXTIHBLKMTBE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yeux sans Visage&lt;/a&gt;_ [Eyes Without a Face], and who not only knew the film, but knew the horror of it, on a deeply personal level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Morris_eyeswithoutaface.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;739&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HUMAN BEINGS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/HUMAN-BEINGS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="illustration" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/illustration/"/>
    
      <category term="criticism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/criticism/"/>
    
      <category term="surrealism" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/surrealism/"/>
    
      <category term="biography" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/biography/"/>
    
      <category term="horror" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/horror/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Magic Flight of Thought</title>
    <link href="https//yunchtime.github.io/IDEAS/the-magic-flight-of-thought/"/>
    <id>https//yunchtime.github.io/IDEAS/the-magic-flight-of-thought/</id>
    <published>2015-02-02T09:43:47.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-19T00:15:02.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://yunchtime.tumblr.com/post/109826887527/the-flight-of-thought-is-no-longer-a-magic-power" target="_blank" rel="external"><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Thor_Bell_sm.png" alt="" width="551" height="409"></a></p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>Today I was talking to my sister (Happy Birthday, Chi!) and we were chatting about the crazy speed of new technology.  How strange it is to collapse our life experience into a series of new devices and how they affected us, and then try to imagine what it is like to be born digital, with all this shiny stuff that has no historical context.  As Peter Goldman said: “Between the twitterverse and the 24-hour cable news cycle our history keeps disappearing.”</p><p><strong>Now, everything is instantaneous, all knowledge is free, one-to-one communication is a such a waste of time…</strong>   “<em>duh!</em>  old timer, how can you be so passé.”</p><p>This got me thinking about the impact of earlier communication technologies and what they were like in the popular culture <strong>before</strong> they were taken for granted.</p><p>What was it like 100 years ago, when the telephone was first established as a fixture of modern life?   In 1880, there had only been 108,000 telephones in use, by 1890 there were 467,000 telephones installed.</p><p>Think of the rapid change as this newfangled device penetrated American society.</p><p><strong>1900</strong> 600,000 (for 76,000,000 people) reaching <strong>0.79%</strong> of the population</p><p><strong>1905</strong> 2,200,000 (for 83,000,000 people) reaching <strong>2.6%</strong> of the population</p><p><strong>1910</strong> 5,800,000 (for 92,000,000 people) reaching <strong>6.3%</strong> of the population</p><p>During the first 25 years of its existence the telephone was physically accessible to less than 1% of the population, but that number nearly tripled between 1900 and 1905, then doubled again, between 1905 and 1910.   This exponential growth, and the exposure of greater and greater numbers of people to this technology &#8212; <em>which could project their voice instantly to almost anywhere</em> &#8212; must indeed have seemed like magic, like something from mythology come to life!</p><p>So it was not surprising to find an advertisement in the 1914 <em>Farm Journal</em> in which the American Telephone and Telegraph Company actually portrayed their service in mythological terms.  AT&amp;T was established only nine years earlier, in 1885, and by 1914 they had been riding a totally unparalleled explosion of telephony…and yet, from their point of view, they had more than 90% of the population left to capture as customers!   How to capture their imagination and then their money?   That must have been the operating question for the AT&amp;T publicity machine of the time.    And here is what they came up with:</p><a id="more"></a><blockquote><p><strong><em>The Magic Flight of Thought</em></strong></p><p><em>Ages ago, Thor, the champion of the Scandinavian gods, invaded Jotunheim, the land of the giants and was challenged to feats of skill by Loki, the king.</em></p><p><em>Thor matched Thialfi, the swiftest of mortals, against Hugi in a footrace.  Thrice they swept over the course, but each time Thialfi was hopelessly defeated by Loki’s runner.</em></p><p><em>Loki confessed to Thor afterwards that he had deceived the god by enchantments, saying, “Hugi was my thought, and what speed can ever equal his?”</em></p><p><em>But the flight of thought is no longer a magic power of mythical beings, for the Bell Telephone has made it a common daily experience.</em></p><p><em><strong>Over the telephone, the spoken thought is transmitted instantly, directly where we send it,</strong> outdistancing every other means for carrying of messages.</em></p><p><em>In the Bell System, the telephone lines reach throughout the country, and <strong>the thoughts of the people are carried with lightning speed in all directions</strong>, one mile, a hundred, or two thousand miles away.</em></p><p><em>And because the Bell System so adequately served the practical needs of the people, the magic of thought’s swift flight occurs 25,000,000 times every twenty-four hours.</em></p></blockquote><p>&nbsp;</p><p>What a fascinating text!    It appeared in <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=stxGAAAAYAAJ&lpg=PA142&ots=mkmgICZJd4&dq=Universal%20Aether%20Telegraph%20Co.%20farm%20journal&pg=PA142#v=onepage&q&f=true" target="_blank"><em>Farm Journal</em>, Feb 1914, p. 142</a>.  Can we be pardoned to take a little semiotic glance at this stuff?    Summoning the gods themselves, Ma Bell pits the champion Thor against the cunning Loki.   Thor, the simple honest hard-working champion, doesn’t think of riding the skies on his <em>uru</em>-hammer, but puts an ordinary mortal on the ground to run the course as his surrogate.  In other words, <strong>Thor cannot think beyond the manifestation of his physical body</strong>, and must toil against gravity, against distance, against steep slopes.   Thor is the eternal mail-carrier, battering his way forward against the snow, the rain, the heat, and gloom of night.  Just as it ever was, since Ancient Persian times, or earlier, the imperative of moving information through physical dimensions of space has decided the fate of humans and their societies.</p><p>By contrast, the wily and diabolical Loki projects his thoughts over the same course, and thoughts &#8212; <em>like electrons!</em> &#8212; travel instantly, leaving no tracks and without muddying the wings of anybody’s sandals.  Here, we can see that Loki transcends the physical body, the physical landscape, with all their sordid geometries and limitations.  <strong>Loki casts off the body in favor of pure instantaneous thought, which can cover any distance without friction &#8212; Loki operates on the astral plane! </strong> And obviously Ma Bell associates with Loki, keep that in mind.</p><p>Now how is the potential customer going to interpret this allegory?    <em>The flight of thought is no longer a magic power of mythical beings, the Bell Telephone has made it a common daily experience.</em>   Let us say they were channeling Arthur C. Clarke from the future, and they could dig the idea that any technology sufficiently advanced cannot be distinguished from magic.  Sure.  It’s just technology, get used to it!   But wait…  <em>over the telephone, spoken thought is transmitted instantly, wherever we direct it</em>.   The telephone transmits “spoken thought.”   What is that?  Isn’t it just speech?   But this is the diabolical cleverness of Ma Bell.   It is the mental activity of thought that is transmitted &#8212; in it’s spoken form, albeit &#8212; but essentially we are engaging not in <em>telephony</em> but in <em>telepathy</em>!</p><p>Let us think back to 1914.  When the telephone was first introduced, it was the hey-day of table rappers, claire-voyants, and theosophists.   But Ma Bell wasn’t hanging around with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helena_Blavatsky" target="_blank">Madame Blavatsky</a> they were delivering telepathy, the instant transmission of spoken thought!   That!  Was real!</p><p>The homespun-wearing reader of the <em>Farm Journal,</em> leaning next to a pot-bellied stove in the barn, must have spit a long arc of chaw at this news!   After having mortgaged the farm to buy a tractor, so they didn’t get put out of business by the Jones’s over yonder, it must have been rather stimulating to think of being the first feller in the county to have instant communication with anyplace on the continent!   Heady stuff indeed.   And it was not a fantasy story, like something you’d read in <a href="http://www.pulpmags.org/popular_page.html" target="_blank"><em>The Popular Magazine</em></a>.   This was now a common daily experience!</p><p>Note that Ma Bell was advertising in <em>Farm Journal</em>, not just the <em>Wall Street Journal</em>.    This was a populist campaign, because they had to hook the 90% of ordinary folks on the telephone.   They had to make them realize that without the advantage of their spoken thoughts zapping instantly to any destination, they were a thing of the past.    But the ad is so ingenious and non-threatening!    It is not the elite with a monopoly on this power, it is <strong>the thoughts of the people carried with lightning speed</strong>.   We are on the side of the masses, then, says the phone company,  because <strong>the Bell System so adequately served the practical needs of the people, the magic of thought’s swift flight occurs 25,000,000 times every twenty-four hours. </strong> </p><p>This is such interesting stuff!  <strong>It is all about empowering the ordinary people, who become part of this vast network of thrumming brain-waves, snapping switchboards, and furious activity.</strong>    <em>Anyone</em> can call <em>anywhere</em>!   Their spoken thoughts projected instantly, making physical delivery of information obsolete.</p><p>On the other hand, I wonder how many phones in those rural general stores were ringing off the hook?   Compared say, to the offices of J. P. Morgan Bank, or the President of the United States.   <strong>Might there actually be some differential in the effectiveness and egalitarianism of this technology?</strong>   After all, it is <em>Loki</em> inviting us to join in, not Thor!   The silver-tongued Loki has, without a doubt, calculated everything in advance!  Loki knows  that dispersing the general cost of the phone system to the wider population it is going to benefit the rich and the powerful &#8212; those who are being <em>sought</em> after and those who <em>benefit</em> from instant transmission of information.</p><p>This problem remains with us today.   The modern <em>Everyman</em> can trade stocks online with Ameri*trade, or some other abomination from hell.   But <em>qui bono, amici</em>?   Think of those instant massive trades that transpire in milliseconds, that are run by the insiders, and that steer the market up and down like a puppet on a string.  And then keep in mind that none of those damned big brokerage houses are going to  pay a penny in fees or taxes on their stolen profits.   Meanwhile, you could take all the day-trading suckers put together &#8212; paying per-transaction brokerage fees &#8212; and they are flushing more money into the system to keep it all going.</p><p>Indeed, when I read this parable of Thor and Loki from 1914, I was not overly critical of the farmers back in the day.   I suspect they knew which way is up, and were not fooled into thinking that the telephone was a life or death necessity.   What strikes me is how similar the deception is, even to the present day.</p><p>Years ago, at a telecoms research conference (which I participated in while working at M.I.T.), some British boffin in the BT labs gave a hyper-ventilated stump speech about augmented reality glasses.   This was in 1999, so more than ten years before we saw actual products that could deliver augmented reality (<em>ala</em> Google glass launched in 2013).   Basically, what he said was that <strong>anyone who didn’t have the augmented reality <em>edge</em>, was dead in the water.</strong>   Who could survive in the shark eat shark world, without knowing instantly the name of the person beside you [from biometric recognition] and know what size shoes they wear, what high school they went to, and if they had knee surgery?   Above all, which knee!   In case you have to kick it, I suppose.   This sort of uber-frenzied and paranoid reality was rather comical to me.   And I enjoyed it tremendously when I happened across <a href="http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/fiction/accelerando/accelerando.html" target="_blank"><em>Accelerando</em></a> in 2005.   But is it really necessary?</p><p>Now that telephone usage is somewhere OVER 100%, the modern Loki and the modern Ma Bell have been supplanted by Internet services, and more insidiously, social media services.   Mark Zuckerberg now considers himself to be connecting the people, to serve them!   To help them!   Nevermind that he sells the identities, the interests, the habits and secrets of his clients to anyone with money.   He is a populist, on a mission to connect all the human beings on the planet in his network of instant spoken thought.</p><p>The “people” who have now become <em>uber</em>-connected freaks &#8212; yes, those 1.3 billion humans who are registered users of Facebook &#8212; aren’t they somewhat addled and hyperactive?   They show all the signs of acute addiction.   So what if all that random babbling is instantly commented on from every part of the globe.   Is it meaningful?  Has the purpose of human life been reduced to the bathos of continuous trivia and virtual contact?</p><p>Somehow the farmer contemplating the future in 1914 doesn’t seem all that bad to me from my laptop screen in 2015.  At least he had some ground to stand on, some pigs to feed, a back field to plow.   And today, what have we got?   A virtual server on shared hosting that we have to update, a linux kernel to patch, and pingback vulnerability to rid of email spam?   This is progress…  <em>feh</em>.</p><p>References:</p><ol><li><p>US Census Bureau, Statistics of Manufactures 1890, Operating Telephone Companies.  <a href="http://www2.census.gov/prod2/decennial/documents/1890d5-13.pdf" target="_blank">link</a></p></li><li><p>Imagining the Internet. Elon University, School of Communications.  <a href="http://www.elon.edu/e-web/predictions/150/1870.xhtml" target="_blank">link</a></p></li><li><p>The U.S. Postal Service Creed <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Postal_Service_creed" target="_blank">link</a></p></li><li><p>Peter Goldman, <em>quoted in Malcolm X Was Right About America</em>. <a href="http://www.commondreams.org/views/2015/02/02/malcolm-x-was-right-about-america" target="_blank">link</a></p></li></ol><p><img class="alignnone" src="http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/loki_facebook.jpg" alt=""></p><p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://yunchtime.tumblr.com/post/109826887527/the-flight-of-thought-is-no-longer-a-magic-power&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;external&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone&quot; src=&quot;http://www.yunchtime.net/misc/Thor_Bell_sm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;551&quot; height=&quot;409&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I was talking to my sister (Happy Birthday, Chi!) and we were chatting about the crazy speed of new technology.  How strange it is to collapse our life experience into a series of new devices and how they affected us, and then try to imagine what it is like to be born digital, with all this shiny stuff that has no historical context.  As Peter Goldman said: “Between the twitterverse and the 24-hour cable news cycle our history keeps disappearing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now, everything is instantaneous, all knowledge is free, one-to-one communication is a such a waste of time…&lt;/strong&gt;   “&lt;em&gt;duh!&lt;/em&gt;  old timer, how can you be so passé.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This got me thinking about the impact of earlier communication technologies and what they were like in the popular culture &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; they were taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was it like 100 years ago, when the telephone was first established as a fixture of modern life?   In 1880, there had only been 108,000 telephones in use, by 1890 there were 467,000 telephones installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of the rapid change as this newfangled device penetrated American society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1900&lt;/strong&gt; 600,000 (for 76,000,000 people) reaching &lt;strong&gt;0.79%&lt;/strong&gt; of the population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1905&lt;/strong&gt; 2,200,000 (for 83,000,000 people) reaching &lt;strong&gt;2.6%&lt;/strong&gt; of the population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1910&lt;/strong&gt; 5,800,000 (for 92,000,000 people) reaching &lt;strong&gt;6.3%&lt;/strong&gt; of the population&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first 25 years of its existence the telephone was physically accessible to less than 1% of the population, but that number nearly tripled between 1900 and 1905, then doubled again, between 1905 and 1910.   This exponential growth, and the exposure of greater and greater numbers of people to this technology &amp;#8212; &lt;em&gt;which could project their voice instantly to almost anywhere&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; must indeed have seemed like magic, like something from mythology come to life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was not surprising to find an advertisement in the 1914 &lt;em&gt;Farm Journal&lt;/em&gt; in which the American Telephone and Telegraph Company actually portrayed their service in mythological terms.  AT&amp;amp;T was established only nine years earlier, in 1885, and by 1914 they had been riding a totally unparalleled explosion of telephony…and yet, from their point of view, they had more than 90% of the population left to capture as customers!   How to capture their imagination and then their money?   That must have been the operating question for the AT&amp;amp;T publicity machine of the time.    And here is what they came up with:&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="IDEAS" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/categories/IDEAS/"/>
    
    
      <category term="memes" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/memes/"/>
    
      <category term="gadgets" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/gadgets/"/>
    
      <category term="telecoms" scheme="https//yunchtime.github.io/tags/telecoms/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
